<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christs communion with his church militant First preached, and now published, for the good of Gods church in generall. By Nicholas Lockyer, Mr. of Arts.</title>
            <author>Lockyer, Nicholas, 1611-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 183 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 108 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06160</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16651</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100760</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836589</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836589</idno>
            <idno type="VID">871</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06160)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 871)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1177:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christs communion with his church militant First preached, and now published, for the good of Gods church in generall. By Nicholas Lockyer, Mr. of Arts.</title>
                  <author>Lockyer, Nicholas, 1611-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20], 194 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. G[riffin] for Iohn Rothwell, at the Sunne in S. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Trinity College (Dublin, Ireland). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Consolation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Spiritual lifex --  Anglican authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:871:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:871:1"/>
            <p>CHRISTS COMMVNION WITH HIS Church Militant. Firſt preached, and
now publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, for the good of Gods Church in generall.</p>
            <p>By. <hi>Nicholas Lockyer,</hi> Mr. of Arts.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Cant. 1.13.</bibl> 
               <p>A bundle of Myrrhe is my well-beloved unto me, he ſhall lye all
night betwixt my breaſts.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. G.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Rot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll,</hi> at the Sunne in S. <hi>Pauls Church-yard.</hi> 1640.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:871:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:871:2"/>
            <head>TO The vertuous Lady, Aunt SUSAN CECILL, Grace and peace be
multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, by <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adam: The ſweet taſte I have had, of your Ladyſhips love
to the beſt things, hath encouraged me, humbly to preſent this little tract
unto you. What <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeakes <pb facs="tcp:871:3"/>from experience, that you
upon triall have found true, <hi>That the most promiſing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of this
life, are vanity and vexation of Spirit.</hi> Our wiſe and mercifull Father,
doth uſually thus imbitter the ſweeteſt things of this world to us, that
we may the more cordially relliſh, and fervently ſeek after, that full
ſatisfying and everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſweetneſſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, which is in
communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with Chriſt our heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Husband, in whom all fulneſſe of
conſolation dwels. A drop of this tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendant fulneſſe, your
La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſhip <pb facs="tcp:871:3"/>(I hope) ſhall finde, diſtilled into your ſoule,
by reading this little worke now come to your hands, which like <hi>Aqua
Vitae,</hi> ſhall cheere and revive your ſad ſpirit, when ready to faint.
Fainting perſons, carry lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle bottles of reviving li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quids, alwayes about
them; if your Ladyſhip ſhal think fit, to make this little Tract, your
pocket-companion, and peruſe a little of it ſtill, when you feele
ſoule-qualmes to ſeaze upon you, you ſhall finde (I truſt) through the
bleſſing of Chriſt, much eaſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; <pb facs="tcp:871:4"/>and ſo
ſpend and end your aged dayes, in more true ſolace of heart, then you have
done your primeſt dayes of flouriſhing youth. The accompliſhing of this,
is the ſincere and holy aime of your much obliged Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew, in this his
firſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering to publick view. Which ſimple aime, that the Lord may
graciouſly anſwer, to your Ladyſhips comfort here, and eternall
happineſſe hereafter, I ſhall ſtill continue my prayer, (though here I
end my Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) that the Lord will ſtill attend this my poore endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour 
<pb facs="tcp:871:4"/>with his rich bleſſing, to all the partakers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and in
ſpeciall to you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your much obliged Nephew, <hi>Nicholas
Lockyer.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:871:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:871:5"/>
            <head>Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ommunion with Chriſt, is our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines in this world, and in
the world to come: that which makes every bitter thing ſweet, and every
ſweet thing ſweeter. With this ſweet ſubject is this little tract, now
come to thy hand, taken up. Poore fallen man is ſtill complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of one
want or other; and when the thing is given which he longed for, yet his ſoule
is as far from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, as before; like to a childe that cries for this and
that, and yet when he hath what he cryed for, continues crying ſtill, and
cannot tell well what he would have. All our want <pb facs="tcp:871:6"/>is this, the want
of Communion with Chriſt: this is the cauſe of all complaints; the
infelicity of the ſoule; the ſumme of mans miſery, here and hereafter;
but poore blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſees it not, and therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines of twenty things,
twenty miles a this ſide his diſeaſe; and ſo ſpends his dayes in
labour and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and yet loſes happineſſe, both here and hereafter
too. A full fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition of Chriſt, is full felicity: a full fruition of any
thing below Chriſt, without Chriſt, is but vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and vexation of
ſpirit. The more then, O fallen man, thou canſt get into communion with thy
God, the more will thy great loſſe bee repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, thy complaining ſoule
ſatisfied, &amp; thy tranquillity ſetled upon thee againe. Hunt not then
after rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, honours, pleaſures, and ſuchlike low delights of the
ſonnes of men, with this deluded miſtaken world, which lyes in
wickedneſſe; for feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city <pb facs="tcp:871:6"/>is not in theſe: but ſtudy and
ſtrive after a nearer communion with Chriſt: the next way to get moſt in
with him, is the ſpeedy way unto all happineſſe: ſo much as thou
canſt get of his company, ſo much art thou in Heaven. <hi>How preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous are
thy thoughts unto mee, O God,</hi> (ſaith David?) <hi>how great is the
ſumme of them? If I ſhould count them, they are more in number then the
ſand: when I awake I am ſtill with thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal.
139.17,18.</note> This is Heaven upon Earth; and that true nobility and honour,
which wee ſhould all bee ambitious after; to loſe our ſpirits in God.
What an unſpeakable felicity is it, to bee ſtill with God in our thoughts?
This ennobles the ſpirit of man, and makes it a companion to the King of
Kings: this gives evenneſſe and ſteadineſſe to a mans courſe; and
makes him walke in all the wayes of God blameleſſe: this gives
tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant <pb facs="tcp:871:7"/>peace &amp; tranquility to a mans ſpirit; and
makes him unmoveable in the midſt of feares: this gives bread, in famine;
drink in drought; peace, in warre; health, in ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; life, in death.
Devote thy ſelfe therefore to Chriſt, that he may devote himſelfe to
thee: and as a poore <hi>medium</hi> of communion, make uſe (if you pleaſe)
of this enſuing Treatiſe. If thou get any good, give glory to God; and make
the poore Pen-man, a conſtant ſharer in thy prayers.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in Chriſt. <hi>Theophilus
Philanthropus.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:871:7"/>
            <head>The Principall Heads hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in this Tract.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THat the Church of Chriſt Militant, ſhall not bee left
comfortleſſe, becauſe Chriſt will come to her, <hi>Pag.</hi> 9</item>
               <item>That Chriſt doth come to his Church Milit. <hi>pag,</hi>
10, 11.</item>
               <item>How Chriſt doth come to his Church Militant, to comfort her
in all conditions, <hi>p.</hi> 18, 19</item>
               <item>When Chriſt comes to his diſconſolate Church, as a
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, <hi>pag.</hi> 41, 42, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Why Chriſt will come to his Church upon earth, as
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, <hi>pag.</hi> 51, 52, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Wicked men ſhall live and <pb facs="tcp:871:8"/>dye comfortleſs,
becauſe Chriſt as a Comforter will never come to them, <hi>p.</hi> 57, 58,
&amp;c.</item>
               <item>Laughter is one thing, and ſpirituall conſolation
another, <hi>p.</hi> 59</item>
               <item>How Chriſt doth come to the wicked in this life,
<hi>p.</hi> 61</item>
               <item>Chriſt will come to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, neither in proſperity
nor in adverſity, as a Comforter, <hi>p.</hi> 62, 63, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>How wicked men may get Christ as a Comforter, to come to
them, <hi>p.</hi> 66, 67, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Vſefull inſtructions to ſtrong men, and to babes in
Chriſt, <hi>p.</hi> 68</item>
               <item>Strong men in Chriſt that <pb facs="tcp:871:8"/>ſay Chriſt as a
Comforter is come to them, ſhould make it ſure to themſelves, that they
are not deluded, <hi>p.</hi> 65.</item>
               <item>The great need of this, <hi>p</hi> 69</item>
               <item>How a man may know that it is Christ indeed, and no ſpirit
of deluſion, which is come to him with conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>p.</hi> 73,
74</item>
               <item>Strong men in Chriſt, after they have made it ſure to
themſelves, that the true Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter is come to them, ſhould ſo walk that
they may ever in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy his ſweet company, <hi>p.</hi> 80</item>
               <item>How Chriſtians may ſo walk as to enjoy Chriſt as a
Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter continually, <hi>p.</hi> 81, 82, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Babes in Chriſt which never <pb facs="tcp:871:9"/>found Chriſt as a
Comforter to come to them, ſhould beleeve that Chriſt will come to them,
<hi>p.</hi> 93</item>
               <item>Their objections againſt Chriſt comming to them as a
Comforter, anſwered, <hi>p.</hi> 93, 94</item>
               <item>Babes in Chriſt that never found Chriſt as a Comforter
come to them, ſhould patiently wait till Chriſt thus come to them,
<hi>p.</hi> 98</item>
               <item>Severall conſiderations very powerfull, to make the ſoule
to wait patiently, till Chriſt as a Comforter come to him, <hi>p.</hi> 98,
99, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Babes in Chriſt, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet found Christ as a
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter come to them, ſhould <pb facs="tcp:871:9"/>obſerve how Chriſt comes with
comfort to the ſoule, and not put him off, <hi>p.</hi> 109, 110</item>
               <item>Babes in Chriſt, which have found Chriſt as a Comforter
to come to them, but now have loſt him, ſhould labour to bee ſenſible
of their loſſe, <hi>p.</hi> 112, 113, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Such ſhould not blame Chriſt for departing as a Comforter
from them, <hi>p.</hi> 116, 117, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Meanes how ſuch babes in Chriſt, may get their Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
to returne againe to them, <hi>p.</hi> 118, 119, &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head> 
                  <q>
                     <bibl>2 Tim. 4. Verſ. 22.</bibl> 
                     <p>The Lord Jeſus Chriſt bee with thy ſpirit.</p>
                  </q>
               </head>
               <item>To have the Lord Ieſus <pb facs="tcp:871:10"/>Chriſt with our
ſpirits, is a prime and principall bleſſing, <hi>p.</hi> 126</item>
               <item>There is a double preſence of Chriſt with man, corporall
and ſpirituall joyntly, or meerely ſpirituall, <hi>p.</hi> 127, 128,
&amp;c.</item>
               <item>The ſpirituall preſence of Chriſt with man upon earth,
is commune or ſpeciall, <hi>p.</hi> 129, 130, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>To have Chriſt ſpecially preſent with our ſpirits, is
the ready way to all temporall good, <hi>p.</hi> 134</item>
               <item>Objections to the contrary, anſwered, <hi>p.</hi> 135, 136,
&amp;c.</item>
               <item>To have Christ ſpecially preſent with our ſpirits, is
the ready way to all ſpirituall <pb facs="tcp:871:10"/>good, <hi>p.</hi> 143, 144,
&amp;c.</item>
               <item>To have Chriſt after a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall manner with our
ſpirits is the ready way to eternall good, <hi>p.</hi> 147</item>
               <item>Not to have Chriſt ſpecially preſent with our ſpirits
is a great evill, <hi>p.</hi> 149</item>
               <item>Wherein this grand evill doth principally conſiſt,
<hi>p.</hi> 149, 150, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>How to know whether Chriſt be ſpecially preſent with
our ſpirits, <hi>p.</hi> 164, 165, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>How to get Chriſt to be ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally preſent with our
ſpirits, <hi>p.</hi> 171, 172, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Men that finde Chriſt ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially preſent with their
ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, ſhould thankfully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge <pb facs="tcp:871:11"/>this great favour
<hi>p.</hi> 176, 177, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Such ſhould labour to keepe Chriſt with their ſpirits,
<hi>p.</hi> 180</item>
               <item>According to what operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, a man may loſe the
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Christ, <hi>p.</hi> 181, 182, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Chriſtians ſhould labour to get Christ as much preſent
with their ſpirits as may bee: and how this may be done: ſee page, 188,
189, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Comfort against the ſword, plague, famine, perſecution,
and the like, ariſeth to them which have Christ ſpecially preſent with
their ſpirits, <hi>p.</hi> 191, 192, &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:871:11"/>
            <head>CHRIST'S COMMUNION with his Church Militant.</head>
            <head> 
               <q>
                  <bibl>John 14. <hi>verſ.</hi> 18.</bibl> 
                  <p>I will not leave you comfortleſſe, I will come to you.</p>
               </q>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HRIST and his Church are deare each to other: the truth of this
is at large manifeſt in this Chapter. Chriſt as a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Husband, being
to leave <pb n="2" facs="tcp:871:12"/>his earthly Spouſe, to wit, his Church Militant,
and to live with his Father at his right hand in glory, with his Church
Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant; endeavoureth in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Verſes of this Chapter, to comfort the
ſad Spirit of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Spouſe, which he percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved was much dejected.
The Verſe which I have choſen to inſiſt on, is one of them: <hi>I will
not leave you comfortleſſe, I will come to you.</hi> In more words let me
repeate this Verſe againe. <hi>Thou O my Love, my Dove, my faire one, art
ſad I ſee and diſconſolate at my departure! As a Lily in the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley;
nay, as a Lily (indeed) among thornes I ſhall leave thee: the Prince of
darkneſſe dwelling in the children of darkneſſe, will endeavour to
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure thee; Sons of Belial will beſet thee, perſecute and torment thee,
as they have done me before thee: but be not at this, O faireſt of women! 
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:871:12"/>dejected, as one without all conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: for I will not
leave thee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe, I will come to thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What difference is there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene a Priſon-houſe and mine own
houſe, if ſweet friends con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually come to me there? Tis a Priſon and
no better, we abide in whileſt we dwell in the body: fetter'd we are with
many luſts; and groane we doe, under the tyranny &amp; oppreſſion of a
body of death; and O! wretched men that wee are dwelling in theſe dungeons of
Clay, if no friend from Heaven come to us? 'Tis true, O my Spouſe, what thou
ſayeſt; and therefore that thy dweling in the body may not be
comfortleſſe, I will come to thee. <hi>I will not leave thee
comfortleſſe, I will come to thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The body is a Priſon to the ſoule, and the World is a Hell to
both. The God of this world <pb n="4" facs="tcp:871:13"/>is a Devill, and the children of
this world Devils, to the Spouſe of Chriſt. The Father torments her
ſpirit, and the Children tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment her fleſh: neither in body nor ſoule,
whileſt in this world, can the Spouſe of Chriſt be qui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>et. We that are
thus in Hell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth, ſhall quickly be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe, if no friend
from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven come to us. True, O my Spouſe: but to prevent this, <hi>I will
come to thee.</hi> From Heaven to Earth (indeed) is a long jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; but yet
this I'le not ſtand on, rather then thou ſhalt be left comfortleſſe, in
any condition upon Earth, I will from Heaven come to thee. Let it bee what
weather 'twill; at what time 'twill; and be at midnight thou need'ſt me, I
will come to thee. <hi>I will not leave you comfortleſſe, I will come to
you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Affliction hath made many <pb n="5" facs="tcp:871:13"/>friends upon Earth
forſake me, O my Saviour! wilt not thou my heavenly friend ſo ſerve mee?
What if the Devill caſt me into Priſon? wilt thou come to mee there? wilt
thou viſit me when I lye in a naſty roome, amongſt naſty wretches, that
curſe and ſwear, which thou canſt not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to heare? Yea, O faireſt
of Women! rather then thou ſhalt be comfortleſſe in ſuch a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<hi>I will come to thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou wilt come to me O my Saviour one day; but what if the Devill
keepe mee in ſuch a Priſon ten dayes? a long time? till the iron enter into
my ſoule? wilt thou not wax weary at laſt, and leave comming to me? No my
love, I am reſolved to the contrary. <hi>[I will not] leave thee
comfortleſſe [I will] come to thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why, but what if Satan win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>now me as wheat, and caſt me 
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:871:14"/>into ſinne, which is more odious to thee then any
priſon; then any place, or any thing: wilt thou not then ſhake me off for
ever, &amp; never come to me more? This O faireſt of Women, may make me
ceaſe comming to thee for a moment, but no longer; for I am reſolved not to
<hi>[leave] thee comfortleſſe</hi> in any condition, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſin or
puniſhment. <hi>I will not [leave] thee comfortleſſe, [I will] come to
thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Text you ſee, is Chriſts conjugall promiſe to his
Spouſe, of all kindneſſe, during the time of his perſonall abſence.
The matter of this promiſe is conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latory; the forme according to which
our Saviour expreſſeth this conſolatory language, is firſt negative,
<hi>I will not leave you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe.</hi> Secondly affirmative, <hi>I
will come to you.</hi> Theſe latter words containe the reaſon of 
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:871:14"/>what is delivered in the former. Wee cannot bee
comfortleſſe; <hi>[becauſe]</hi> Chriſt ſtill comes to us. And thus
taking the words, you may reade them thus, viz. <hi>I will not leave you
comfortleſſe,</hi> [for] <hi>I will come to you.</hi> No condition can bee
comfortleſſe, if Chriſt come to us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will not leave you comfortleſſe,]</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>I will not leave you
fatherleſſe and motherleſſe, I wil not leave you Orphants,</hi> ſaith
the Originall, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the word comes
from, that is here tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>comfortleſſe,</hi> which ſignifies,
to be made fatherleſſe and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs; which becauſe it is uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
a condition very comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, therefore is the word thus rendered
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>comfortleſſe.</hi> Thus
the children of Chriſt ſhall not be left. They are no <hi>Orphans</hi>
which have Chriſt for their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. They are never totally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reft 
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:871:15"/>of all comfort, to whom Chriſt comes: and thus he will
ſtill do to his Church Millitant Chriſt will never leave com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from
Heaven to Earth, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it bee a very long jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, as long as he hath any
one childe upon Earth. <hi>I will not leave you comfortleſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will come to you,]</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I returne to you ſaith the
Originall; ſpoken in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent tenſe, and not in the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>[I
will] returne to you,</hi> as we have it tranſlated. <hi>Ac ſi diceret
Chriſtus</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>ſe licèt non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum profectum, jam
eſſe inreditu</hi> As if Chriſt had ſaid, although I am not yet gone
from you, yet am I returning to you. Chriſt though not actually in perſon
departed, yet was ready in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to be preſent with his Spouſe to the end
of the world.</p>
            <p>Thus having Paraphraſtical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <pb n="9" facs="tcp:871:15"/>gone over
theſe words, I will put the plaine meaning of them into this
<hi>Theſis</hi> in divinity. <hi>That the Church of Chriſt Militant,
ſhall not bee left comfortleſſe, becauſe Chriſt will come to
her.</hi> Or thus, <hi>No Childe of Chriſt upon Earth, ſhall be left
comfortleſſe, for Chriſt will come to him.</hi> What Chriſt ſpake at
his departure to his Diſciples, was not for them only, but for the comfort of
all his people to the end of the world. In his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples hee ſpake thus to
all his children, that are or ever ſhall be upon the face of the Earth, <hi>I
will not leave you comfortleſſe, I will come to you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This comfortable doctrine, that I may fully and methodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally
handle, I will lay open un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you theſe foure things: Firſt, that Chriſt
doth come to his children upon Earth. Secondly, how Chriſt doth come to his 
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:871:16"/>children upon Earth. Thirdly, when Chriſt doth come to
his children upon Earth. Laſtly, why Chriſt will take ſo much paines, as
to come to his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren on Earth? I begin with the firſt of theſe, to wit,
that Chriſt doth come to his Church and children upon Earth. The truth of
this is evident by our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours own language, and by each godly mans
evidence.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour not only in my Text, but in many other places
promiſed to come to his Church Militant, and therefore ſurely he doth come
to his people on Earth: for Chriſt is God, <hi>and God cannot lye nor
repent.</hi> What Chriſt hath ſaid, he will do, that he will faithfully
performe to a tittle: <hi>for faithfull is he that hath promiſed,</hi>
ſaith the Apoſtle. <hi>Go therefore &amp; teach all Nations, &amp;c.
Teaching them to obſerve all things, <pb n="11" facs="tcp:871:16"/>whatſoever I have
commanded you; and loe I am with you alwayes, even to the end of the world,
Amen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19,10.</note> This place
ſhewes plainly that Chriſt doth come to his children upon Earth; and that
he will do this to the end of the world. For Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters (of all men) to walke
faithfully in their places, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their flock to <hi>obſerve [all]
things, that Chriſt hath given them in charge,</hi> will coſt them hot
wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, eſpecially living in corrupt places. This our Saviour tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
conſider'd; and therefore that his Diſciples might not be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartn'd,
he aſſures them of his company unto the laſt, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and comfort
them. <hi>Loe I am with you to the end of the world</hi> Chriſt by this
phraſe of ſpeech, doth hint us, that what he then ſpake, ſhould reach
further then unto thoſe to whom he then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared: namely, to all Miniſters
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:871:17"/>and people <hi>to the end of the world,</hi> that ſhall
faithfully diſcharge their places and callings to his honour.</p>
            <p>I might here tell you, that not only Chriſts word, but alſo
Chriſts name ſets forth the truth of this, that Chriſt is with his Church
Militant, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, that he doth come to her. He was called
<hi>Emmanuel,</hi> which being interpreted, <hi>Is God with us.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi>
1.23.</note> Which name was not only to note Chriſt, as then cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally
preſent with his Church, but to note Chriſt as one ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving actually
aſſumed our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſo to be more gloriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſent with his
Church to the end of the world, then ever before from the beginning after
<hi>Adams</hi> fall. Now as ſhe ſaid of her Husband, <hi>as his name is,
ſo is he; Nabal is his name, and folly is with him:</hi> ſo may the
Spouſe <pb n="13" facs="tcp:871:17"/>ſpeak of her Husband Chriſt; as his name is,
ſo is he. <hi>Emmanuel</hi> is his name; which ſignifies <hi>God with
us,</hi> and ſo indeed, is Chriſt. He is continually with us. What
<hi>David</hi> ſaid of himſelfe, in reſpect of Chriſt, that may we
truly ſay of Chriſt, in reſpect of us. <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe</hi>
(ſaith he) <hi>I am conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually with thee; thou haſt holden me by my right
hand.</hi> Though Chriſt dwell in Heaven, and wee on Earth, yet
nevertheleſſe hee is continually comming to us, and abiding with us.</p>
            <p>The godly have and do finde the truth of this by bleſſed
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, which is the ſecond thing; and that which I rather inſiſt
on, for the confirmation of the truth in hand: becauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt experience
there is no diſputation. <hi>Peter</hi> found the truth of this, that
Chriſt comes to his children upon Earth, that <pb n="14" facs="tcp:871:18"/>their
condition may not be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe. <hi>Herod</hi> caſt <hi>Peter</hi>
into Priſon, and thought to have made him comfortleſſe; but Chriſt came
to him, as you may ſee. <hi>And behold</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>the Angell
of the Lord came upon him, and a light ſhined in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and he
ſmote Peter on the ſide, and raiſed him up, ſaying, Ariſe up quickly,
and his chaines fell off from his hands.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi>
12.7.</note> The Jewes by a ſtorme of Stones, thought to have made
<hi>Steven</hi> comfortleſſe, but Chriſts comming to him prevented.
Chriſt ſo gloriouſly came to him in that deadly ſtorme, that he found
more comfort then (I beleeve) then ever hee did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in his life: for <hi>he
looked up ſtedfaſtly into Heaven, and ſaw the glory of God, and Ieſus
ſtanding at the right hand of God:</hi> he ſaw the Heavens opened ready to
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him, which tranſcendant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <pb n="15" facs="tcp:871:18"/>revived him which
glorious viſion he could never have ſeen, had not Chriſt come to him.
<hi>Paul</hi> likewiſe found the truth of this point, when he had left
<hi>Athens,</hi> and came to preach to the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> at
<hi>Corinth.</hi> He was very fearfull, what ſucceſſe he ſhould finde
in his Miniſtery, amongſt the barbarous <hi>Gentiles.</hi> Now our tender
Saviour, that <hi>Paul</hi> might not bee overborne with feare, and made
heartleſſe and comfortleſſe, graciouſly comes to him in a viſion,
as you may read. <hi>Then ſpake the Lord to Paul by night in a viſion, Be
not afraid, but ſpeak and hold not thy peace; for I am with thee; and no man
ſhall ſet on thee to hurt thee, for I have much people in this
City.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 18.9</note> Thus at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time
Chriſt came to <hi>Paul,</hi> that he might not be left com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe,
when he was pleading his cauſe before <hi>Anomias,</hi> and 
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:871:19"/>like to be pull'd in pieces. <hi>And the night
following</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>the Lord ſtood by him, and ſaid, bee
of good cheere Paul, for as thou haſt teſtified of me in Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem ſo
muſt thou alſo beare witneſſe at Rome.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 23.11</note> At another time <hi>Paul</hi> and
<hi>Silas</hi> together had experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of this truth, that Chriſt comes to
his Church Militant. As they were powring out their ſoules together in
prayer, Chriſt wonderfully came to them: he came in an Earthquake, and made
the <hi>foundations of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhake,</hi> and ſo <hi>opened all the
pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon doores, and looſed every priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners bonds.</hi> Comfortable was
Chriſts comming to <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las,</hi> but terrible to the
Goaler; for he ſeeing in what manner Chriſt broke in and reſcued his
ſervant, would have killed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; but Chriſt came graciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to
his ſoule alſo, and reſcu'd <pb n="17" facs="tcp:871:19"/>it out of the hands of
the Devill. Happy was it for this man, that Chriſt did finiſh two workes in
one journey; to wit, come to <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> and deliver their
bodies out of Priſon, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all come to their Goaler and deliver his
ſoule out of Priſon too. In an Earthquake Chriſt came both to Priſoners
&amp; Goa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler: for the Goaler came <hi>trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling</hi> to the Priſoners of
hope, as a man in deſpaire; <hi>and fell downe,</hi> ſaith the Text,
<hi>before Paul and Silas.</hi> 'Tis no matter how Chriſt come to us, ſo he
comfort us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee leave us. Thus I have ſhewed to you, that Chriſt
doth come to his Church Militant.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing that I am to ſhew you, for the opening of the
point, is, how Chriſt doth come to his Church Militant. To this I will
anſwer, Firſt, more generally, and briefly: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <pb n="18" facs="tcp:871:20"/>more particularly and fully. More generally and briefly, I anſwer
thus; Chriſt viſits his Church Militant, as <hi>David</hi> viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp;
comforted <hi>Hanun,</hi> to wit, mediately by his ſpirit, as <hi>David</hi>
did mediately by his ſervants. <hi>And I wil pray the Father, &amp; he ſhal
give you another Comforter, that he may abide with you for ever; even the
[Spirit of truth,] &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi>
14.16,17.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> found the truth of this, that Chriſt by his
Spirit comes now to his Church Militant. <hi>While Peter thought on the
viſion, [the Spirit] ſaid unto him, behold three men ſeek thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in the ſecond place, that I may more particularly and fully
anſwer to this queſtion, to wit, how Chriſt doth come to his Church
Militant to comfort her in all conditions; I will lay before you the generall
condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of mankinde, and ſhew you <pb n="19" facs="tcp:871:20"/>how Chriſt by his
Spirit, as a Comforter, comes to us in them. The general conditions of
man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde are two, <hi>proſperity</hi> and <hi>adverſity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Proſperity would ſoon bring the ſoules of Gods people, to a
comfortleſſe condition, did not Chriſt by his Spirit come to them. Satan,
that evill Spirit is ſo buſie, comming to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, when in
proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that did not Chriſt alſo come to them by his Almighty
Spirit, to quench all his fiery darts, their ſoules would ſoone be
comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, the Lord knowes. When <hi>Peter</hi> was warme in the High
Prieſts Hall, then the Devill by a Damoſell came to him, and ſo far he
prevail'd on him, that had not Chriſt lookt back upon him, and by his Spirit
come to him, he had beene in a comfortleſſe condition indeed. And thus 
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:871:21"/>would the condition of good men now be, which are warme in
their neſts with outward things, did not Chriſt come to them: when the
ſons of God be honourable, and great amongſt the ſons of men, as
<hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon, Iob<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Iacob,</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi>
were; then the Devill in point of polity, though not out of love, viſits them
often; and by often comming to them then, drawes their precious ſoules in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
many ſins, as pride, ambition, malice, ſenſuality, and the like; which
like Cankers, quickly fret and eat out all divine conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the
ſoule, and leave it like the Prodigall feeding upon husks; ſolacing it
ſelfe with no other joy &amp; content, then what the bare creature dipt in
ſin, will afford the ſenſe; which you muſt needs ſay, is of all
comfortleſſe conditions, the moſt and worſt <pb n="21" facs="tcp:871:21"/>comfortleſſe. Now that theſe may not be left in this
comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſtate, to periſh eternally, Chriſt by his Spirit, thus
comes to them. Firſt in a ſweet ſtill voice behinde them, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
ſpeaks, ſaying, ſometimes, in the midſt of their ſenſuality; this
is not the way to eternall joy: no, this is the way, O ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall ſoule!
walk in it. This ſtill voice ſtrikes a damp in the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſenſuall
foule of a Chriſtian, &amp; makes his heart, in the midſt of vaine
laughter, ſad. If this be not prevalent enough to turne him, but on againe he
will in his ſinfull way; then Chriſt comes with a witneſſe, in
thundering and lightning, to convince and ſting the conſcience, as he did
to the Iſraelites, to bring them to ſee their wickedneſſe in chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
a King. Untill God thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd and lighten'd from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <pb n="22" facs="tcp:871:22"/>fearfully, they layd not to heart their rejecting God as their King,
but went on ſtrongly and unaffectedly in their way. And juſt thus oft times
it is, with many of the Sonnes of God in proſperity: the ſtill voice of
Chriſt ſweetly ſuggeſting, and mildely checking for fin, is not
ſtrong enough to ſtop and turne them; untill the Angell of the Covenant
come downe into the conſcience, and ſtand with a fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Sword, threatning
no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Hell and Death, if they make on a ſteppe further, they ſtop
nor turne not; which though not Chriſts naturall car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage to his children,
yet he will in tender love, deny himſelfe thus farre, as to put on an
af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighting Vizard upon his ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling countenance, and come ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly, and
ſave violently, by plucking his children out of the <pb n="23" facs="tcp:871:22"/>fire,
rather then hee will leave any of his ſo comfortleſſe, as to periſh
remedileſſe. Chriſt will ſpeak out and ſpeak plaine, as he did to
<hi>David</hi> by <hi>Nathan,</hi> when a ſtill voice, and ſecret ſilent
hints and becks will not do. He will come and lay his mouth to a mans eare and
cry aloud, when he perceives that the pleaſure or profit of ſin, hath made
him very deafe: he will never leave crying and calling, ſtriking and
knocking, till he hath made the deafe ſoule heare, and humble himſelfe with
<hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> and then he puls off the terrible Vizard
from his countenance, and lookes upon the mourning penitent, with a countenance
like <hi>Lebanon,</hi> and his lips drop ſweet ſmelling myrrh, into his
broken ſpirit, and ſo is not left co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortleſſe, according to Chriſts
promiſe, <hi>I will not leave you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe, <pb n="24" facs="tcp:871:23"/>I
will come to you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe Satan ſhould not be buſie, comming to the
ſons of God in proſperity; yet would worldly proſperity be a
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe condition, ſhould not Chriſt by his Spirit come to them.
Riches and honours, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with all other delights of the Sonnes of Men,
they are as the white of an Egge, things without ſavour, unleſſe Chriſt
come along with them to us: they tyre and weary, prick, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract and vex a
man: they rob him of his ſleepe, and many times of his wits, nay, of his
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious life: they drowne mens ſoules in pride, voluptuouſneſſe,
ſecurity, and ſo ſet them in the next way to Hell. This ſnare waits at
every ungodly mans ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which makes proſperity to him comfortleſſe.
This Snare that it may not catch the godly, <pb n="25" facs="tcp:871:23"/>Chriſt comes
to them by his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and ſanctifies proſperity to them; <hi>he teaches
them how to a bound;</hi> that is, how ſo to uſe the creature, as to enjoy
ſervice and comfort from it, and to bring honour and glory to God by it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The creature is empty of what it promiſeth; and entiſing
with what it hath:</hi> and this makes proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to every carnall man, a
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe condition. Now to take off both theſe, Chriſt comes to
his children which enjoy the creature plenteouſly: he comes in the creature,
and ſo cures the emptineſſe of it: that is, by his bleſſing he makes
it ſatisfiable and contentfull to the enjoyer, which it is not of it ſelfe:
this is the peculiar gaine that attends the godly; Chriſt comes in the
creature to them, and ſo cures the emptineſſe of it, and puts ſuch a
ſupernaturall vertue and <pb n="26" facs="tcp:871:24"/>ſweetneſſe in it, that
<hi>they are therewith contented.</hi> And as Chriſt comes <hi>[in]</hi> the
creature to cure the emptineſſe of it, ſo hee comes <hi>[with]</hi> the
creature, to cure the entiſing of it. He doth by the creature leade the
ſoules of his children to the Creator: by the ſweet of the one, he lifts up
their ſoules to Heaven, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the ſweetneſs of the other: ſo that,
that which others are entiſed and beſotted with, and reſt in, that they
take wing from to flee to Heaven, from whence comes every good and perfect
gift, which is that indeed that makes proſperity a comfortable condition;
which otherwiſe is comfortleſſe enough, the Lord knowes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, adverſity would be a comfortleſſe condition to the
godly, if Chriſt by his Spirit did not come to them: This I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe 
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:871:24"/>none will deny; <hi>for no affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in it ſelfe is
comfortable or joyfull,</hi> but comfort leſſe, if Chriſt by his Spirit
do not come to us. Corporall affliction is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe condition,
unleſſe Chriſt come to us, and be our Phyſitian. Spirituall affliction
is a more comfortleſſe conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if Chriſt do not come to us.</p>
            <p>Here theſe two queſtions are neceſſary to be anſwered:
Firſt, how doth Chriſt come to us in corporall affliction? Secondly, how
doth Chriſt come to us in ſpirituall affliction?</p>
            <p>To theſe queſtions both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether I thus anſwer: Chriſt
the Phyſitian of ſoule and body, comes to both with comfort in one way; and
that is by helping the ſoule to apply the promiſes of God, which are
ſuitable to his diſtreſſe. If a childe of God be ſad and
ſorrowfull, becauſe <pb n="28" facs="tcp:871:25"/>of corporall affliction, Chriſt
comes to him by his Spirit, with this comfortable language, <hi>I am
all-ſufficient.</hi> Chriſt by his Spirit, ſpreads abroad this Cardinall
promiſe before the ſad ſoule, and ſhewes him what a depth of mercy is
foulded up in it. There is a ſufficiency of wiſdome in me, to find out
wayes and means to deliver thee, though never ſo low brought. There is
likewiſe a ſufficiency of power, to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute right meanes to
accompliſh their right end. Nay, there is a ſufficiency of power in me, to
work about good for thee, O ſad ſoule, without meanes. There's a
ſufficiency of affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and will, to declare power and wiſdome, with
every Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute elſe, for thy good. If for all this application and
amplifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a generall promiſe, the ſoule ſtill droope under ſome
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:871:25"/>corporall calamity; Chriſt doth then in ſuch a ſoule,
as <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſons and daughters did for him, <hi>They all roſe
up</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>and comforted him:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.35.</note> ſo Chriſt by his Spirit after a
lively manner indeed, riſes up in ſuch a ſoule to comfort him: and now
hee leads this mourning Chriſtian, to ſome particular promiſe; that is,
ſuch a promiſe as ſpeaks not of deliverance in generall, but of
deliverance in particular, out of this or that kinde of diſtreſſe, which
he groanes under. As to give you an inſtance, ſuppoſe a Chriſtian be
ſad &amp; take thought as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>what he ſhall eat, what he
ſhall drinke, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall he ſhall be cloathed:</hi> then the
Comforter comes with this particular promiſe, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſpeakes of deliverance
out of this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular diſtreſſe. <hi>Firſt, ſeeke the Kingdome of
God and his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe <pb n="30" facs="tcp:871:26"/>and all theſe things
ſhall be added unto you: take therefore no thought for to morrow, for to
mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſhall take thought for the things of it ſelfe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.33,34.</note> If yet for all this, the ſpirit of
a Chriſtian ſtill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, as one fearing he ſhall want daily bread
for him and his; then the Comforter comes, and perſwades the ſoule to
reſt quietly upon the promiſe of God. Hee ſpeakes now to the complaining
Chriſtian, as the Levits father in law did to him, <hi>Comfort thy ſelfe I
pray thee, with a morſell of bread.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudges</hi>
19.</note> Comfort thy ſelfe O mourning ſoule, I pray thee, with this
particular pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, which is but a morſell of that bread, which came downe
from Heaven, one of the leaſt favours that Chriſt hath procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for thee,
to wit, a right and intereſt in the creature: with this perſwaſive
language, doth <pb n="31" facs="tcp:871:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>Chriſt follow the complaining
ſoule, untill he hath perſwaded him, to own his own mercy and ſo he keeps
his children in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, from being comfortleſſe.</p>
            <p>As Chriſt in corporall affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions comes to his children, and
keeps them from being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe; ſo likewiſe he comes to them in
ſpirituall afflictions, that they may not be left com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe. If a
childe of God be ſad and ſorrowfull, becauſe of this or that ſtrong
temptation, the Comforter then comes to him with this ſweet language, <hi>My
grace is ſufficient for thee.</hi> Thou prayeſt, and Satan tempts thee;
thou doeſt faſt and pray, and yet Satan and thy luſts are more violent
upon thee: thou doeſt all this with bitter teares, and Satan is the more
bitterly bent againſt thee, and thou art foil'd every moment. By this, O 
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:871:27"/>winnowed ſoule! Chriſt would ſhew thee, that thou
wilt bee comfortleſſe, in the midſt of all thy ſore ſoule-labour,
unleſſe he come to thee. <hi>This ſame ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort us, concerning
the work and toile of our hands,</hi> ſaid <hi>Lamech</hi> of <hi>Noah:</hi>
ſo may we ſay of Chriſt; this ſame muſt comfort us, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the
labour and toile of our ſoules with any temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or elſe we ſhall be
comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, though we labour never ſo much: and this Chriſt doth and
will do, <hi>I will not leave you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe, I will come to
you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If a Chriſtian lye languiſhing, becauſe of Satans prevailing
up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him by temptation; that hee may not be comfortleſſe in this
condition, Chriſt by his Spirit comes to him, and ſhews him the fountaine
of his blood, how deep it is, &amp; how free it is. 
<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 1.7.</note> How deepe it is, that it will
drowne <pb n="33" facs="tcp:871:27"/>all ſin. 
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.7.</note> Sins after
converſion, as well as before: ſinnes often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, as well as ſins
once only committed. And then he ſhewes the wounded ſoule, how free this
fountaine is, for <hi>any that hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and thirſt for it, for any that are
weary and heavie laden,</hi> and deſire to be eaſed by it; and ſo by
degrees drawes the woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſoule, to waſh his wounds in it by faith, and
ſo Chriſt heales and comforts him. As the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of <hi>Ephraim</hi>
comforted him, when he mourned becauſe the men of <hi>Gath</hi> had ſlaine
his ſons.<note place="margin">I <hi>Chro.</hi> 7.22.</note> So Chriſt comes
to us, and comforts us, when the Devill by his temptations hath almoſt
ſlaine our ſoules, hee like the good Samaritan, powres in oyle and wine
into our wounds, and cures us. Though Satan paſſe by, and his limmes
paſſe by, and leave us comfortleſſe, in the day <pb n="34" facs="tcp:871:28"/>of
our wounds and bleeding, yet Chriſt cannot, ſo full of bowels is he, nor
will not, <hi>I will not leave you comfortleſſe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If a Chriſtian lye languiſhing, becauſe of often and
frequent relapſes, after promiſes and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes to do better; If this
Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian in the anguiſh of his ſpirit ſpeak to every godly friend, as
the Prophet did to his, <hi>Therefore ſaid I, look away from me, I will weepe
bitterly, labour not to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort me, becauſe of the ſpoiling of the
Daughter of my people;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> 12.4.</note>
Looke away from me O ye my Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an friends! yea, and you my faithfull
Miniſter; for I will weepe bitterly, labour not to comfort mee, becauſe of
the ſpoiling of my ſoule, by ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſinning, againſt vowes and
promiſes, favours and bleſſings: Chriſt comes to this ſoule, and will
not leave him comfortleſſe <pb n="35" facs="tcp:871:28"/>in this condition, (though
it be indeed a very deſperate condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.) The Comforter uſually takes this
courſe, with this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe ſoule, to powre in ſome oyle into his
deepe wounds: he reaſoneth with him from the mercy of man, to the mercy of
God; from a drop to the Ocean; and it may be, faſtens upon his own language
once delivered to <hi>Peter. Peter came to our Saviour and ſaid,
Lord, how oft ſhall my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſin againſt me, and I forgive him? till
ſeven times? Ieſus ſaith unto him, I ſay not unto thee untill ſeven
times, but untill ſeventy times ſeven.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.21,22,</note> From this ſpeech, the Comforter
thus reaſoneth, with this ſaid and ſore wounded ſoule, viz If Chriſt
would have <hi>Peter,</hi> a ſinfull man, ſhew ſo much mercy to one, ſo
often of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending him; ſurely Chriſt a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God, and infinite in love, is 
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:871:29"/>ready to ſhew much more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion himſelfe, to
thoſe that are penitent, though they have ſinned times without number
againſt him. Thus the Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter leades this deſperate Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, as a
weak wounded man by the hand, from the mercy of man, to the mercy of God, and
enables him this way, after ſome ſpace of time, to take in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: for
Chriſt is reſolved, he will not leave this Chriſtian comfortleſſe.
Chriſt will never leave comming to this comfort leſſe ſoule, with this
ſpeech of his to <hi>Peter,</hi> and others of like nature (as Chriſt is
well furniſht for a Comforter) untill he hath brought him to drink willingly
(for Chriſt forceth no Phyſick upon any Patient) of the cup of
conſolation more or leſſe; and the longer ſick ſoules turn away their
heads from this cup, the <pb n="37" facs="tcp:871:29"/>more (many times) he perſwades
them to drink, at laſt.</p>
            <p>If Chriſt <hi>tentandi gratiâ</hi> for trials ſake, hide
himſelfe from a Chriſtian, &amp; ſo ſet him a mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. I ſhall
ſhew you by and by, how he comes to him. This is a condition (though of all
deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted conditions, the beſt) which will make a Chriſtian heart
comfortleſſe indeed. <hi>Thou didſt hide thy face, and I was
troubled.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.7.</note> Gods hiding his
face, though but for trials ſake, will ſo trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a Chriſtian, that hee
will quickly be a burthen to himſelf, <hi>and feare round about,</hi> as 'tis
ſaid of <hi>Paſhur.</hi> 'Twill make him weary of the night, and weary of
the day; weary of his owne houſe, &amp; weary of Gods houſe; weary of
mirth, and account it madneſſe; weary of riches, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, yea life it
ſelfe, and wiſh for death. <hi>O that I might have my <pb n="38" facs="tcp:871:30"/>requeſt, and that God would grant me the thing that I long for, even
that it would pleaſe God to deſtroy me, that he would let his hand looſe
and cut mee off, then ſhould I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et
have comfort:</hi> then ſhould I ſee the face of God, which I long like
<hi>Moſes</hi> to ſee; then would he lift up the light of his loving
countenance, and cauſe his face to ſhine gloriouſly upon me, whereas now
I walke in the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſhadow of death; dark dayes are all that goe over
my head; the glorious Sunne of righteouſneſſe ſhines not upon my
ſoul, from morning to night. To this ſad ſoule thus bemoan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe
for want of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, Chriſt his well beloved thus comfortably comes.
<hi>There hath no temptation taken hold on thee yet, O mourning ſoule, but
that which is common to man: and be aſſured of this, that God is faithfull 
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:871:30"/>by whom thou art tempted, and will not try thee above that
which thou art able: but with the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion alſo make a way to eſcape,
that ye may be able to beare it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
10.19.</note> For a moment O faireſt of Women; I ſay, juſt cauſe to
hide my face from thee, to try the truth of thy love to me; but know, that with
everlaſting kindneſſe will I have mercy on thee. Thy dulneſſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
in my ſerice, and thy low-priſing my company, did ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing trouble me;
but know, <hi>that the mountaines ſhall depart, and the hils bee removed, but
my kindneſſe ſhall never depart from thee: for this is as the waters of
Noah unto me; as I have ſworne that the waters of Noah, ſhould no more go
over the Earth; ſo have I ſworne that I will not be wroth with thee, nor
rebuke thee. O thou affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and toſſed with tempeſt, and not
comforted, behold I will lay thy <pb n="40" facs="tcp:871:31"/>ſtones with faire
colours, and lay thy foundations with Saphirs, and I will make thy windowes of
Agats, and thy gates of Carbuncles, and all thy borders of pleaſant
Saphirs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> 45.8,9.</note> Out of this
ſweet language of the Prophet to the naturall branch, the Comforter will
fetch ſuch precious water of life, to revive this deſerted ſoule: with
theſe kiſſes of his lips will he ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort him, that he ſhall be
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to ſay with <hi>David, Thou which haſt ſhewed me great
trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, haſt quickned me againe, and haſt brought me up againe from the
depths of the Earth; thou haſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed my joy and comforted me on every
ſide.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71.6.</note> I could hitherto O
my God, ſee thy back-parts; ſome ſad attributes of power and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,
which did terrifie my ſoul to look on; but loe now I ſee thy glory, thou
haſt cauſed it gloriouſly to paſſe by me, nay, <pb n="41" facs="tcp:871:31"/>to
ſhine upon me: I ſee thy face like Lebanon, comely as the Cedars; and
herewith is my longing ſoule ſatisfied, as with marrow and fatneſſe.
<hi>This is my comfort, in mine affliction, for thy Spirit O Chriſt, by thy
word hath revived mee.</hi> So that this ſoule, though very ſorrowfull, yet
is not left comfortleſſe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Thus I have anſwered the ſecond
<hi>Quaere</hi> to wit, how Chriſt comes to us.</p>
            <p>The third thing that I am to ſhew you, is, when Chriſt comes
to us. <hi>I will not leave you comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, I will come to you.</hi> But
when, O my Saviour, wilt thou come to us? To this I anſwer firſt more
generally, then more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly and determinately. More generally and
briefly, I anſwer thus, Chriſt is already come, and is preſent with his
Church Militant, and will be to <pb n="42" facs="tcp:871:32"/>the end of the world, as
hath beene already proved. <hi>I am come into my garden, my Siſter, my
Spouſe, I have gathered my Mirrh with my Spice; I have eaten my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney combe
with my honey: I have drunke my wine with my milke.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.1.</note> Chriſt we ſee by this ſweet
lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, is come, and is with us already. <hi>I am come, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when will he come to me in particular, as a Comforter? this is
the queſtion. To this I anſwer firſt negatively, then po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively.
Negatively I anſwer thus: viz. Chriſt doth not come to us in this valley of
teares, as <hi>Aaron</hi> was commanded to come into the holy place: <hi>Let
him not come at all times,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>leſt he die.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Levit.</hi> 16.2</note> If Chriſt ſhould not come to us at
all times of our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, we ſhould die under our burthen, ſo
comfortleſſe would be our condition. When my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <pb n="43" facs="tcp:871:32"/>is
afflicted, I ſhall be comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, if Chriſt doe not come to me. When
my ſoule is afflicted, I ſhall be more comfortleſſe, if Chriſt doe
not graciouſly come to mee. When my head akes, teeth akes, back akes, or
belly akes: yea, when my leaſt finger, or joynt in my body akes, I ſhall be
comfortleſſe, unleſſe Chriſt come to me, ſo dolorous and
comfortleſſe a creature is man.</p>
            <p>Wherefore as a poſitive an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, to the queſtion ere-while
propoſed, know, that Chriſt comes to his Church militant, at all times: as
long as his people live in this valley of teares, and are in any
diſtreſſe of ſoule or body. He comes to them in proſperity, to
ſweeten that, or elſe there would be but a little comfort and ſweetneſs
in it: but he comes to them in all adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, after a more ſpeciall
man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <pb n="44" facs="tcp:871:33"/>to ſweeten that, being of it ſelfe very bitter;
bitterneſſe in the abſtract: my meaning is, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together bitter, without
the leaſt ſweetneſſe or pleaſure in it, to ſoule or body: for no
afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is in the leaſt manner or mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure joyous, but as Chriſt, by
his kind comming to us then, makes it ſo.</p>
            <p>But here I ſhall be thus que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned: <hi>viz,</hi> if
Chriſt as a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter comes to his Church Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litant, in every
diſtreſſe of ſoule and body; how is it that many of Gods children, in
corporall and ſpirituall afflictions, utter comfortleſſe and
hopeleſſe lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, as thoſe that finde no Comforter come to them?
<hi>Is thy mercy cleane gone, and haſt thou forgotten to be gracious,</hi>
ſaith <hi>David, haſt thou ſhut up thy loving kindneſſe in
diſpleaſure, and wilt thou be no more intreated, &amp;c.</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny 
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:871:33"/>ſuch like ſad and dolorous complaints are ſtill
uttered by ſome of Gods deare children: now if Chriſt as a Comforter, come
to his in every diſtreſſe, why is it thus with theſe?</p>
            <p>To this I will give anſwer firſt more indirectly thus.
Poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly that ſoule which thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines, cannot but confeſſe that
Chriſt hath come and tender'd comfort to him, though hee through anguiſh
and unbeliefe refus'd it. Now if our ſoule-Phyſitian come from Heaven to us
and brings Cordials for us, and we will not take them, but caſt them behinde
ourbacks; ſhall our Phyſitian bee blamed for unfaithfulneſſe and
negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence towards his Patients, as one that did not viſit them?</p>
            <p>Againe, poſſibly too, this ſoul which thus complaines,
muſt confeſſe that Chriſt came to <pb n="46" facs="tcp:871:34"/>him, at the very
beginning of his untractablenes towards God, and told him that this would
quickly bring him into a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe condition, if not timely lookt unto;
and bid him againe and againe, by a ſweet ſtill voice behinde him, to be
more pliable to God, as hee tendered his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and his owne comfort.
Chriſt came to his Spouſe, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Open to me my Siſter, my Love,
my Dove, my faire one, for my head is filled with dew, and my lockes with the
drops of the night.</hi> But though Chriſt thus kindly came to his Spouſe,
yet ſhe unkindly put him off, and upon the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter no better then ſlighted
him. <hi>I have put off my coat, how ſhall I put it on? I have waſhed my
feet, how ſhall I defile them? &amp;c.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of this untractable
carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, Chriſt departed from his Spouſe, and then ſhe made many 
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:871:34"/>complaints: <hi>I opened to my Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but he had
withdrawne him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and was gone.</hi> The Spouſe could not now truly
ſay, that Chriſt had not come to her; but ſhe might truly ſay, that he
did come to her, but ſhee ſlighted him, and therefore he was forc'd to
leave her. Thus 'tis with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny now. They mourne like <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel</hi> in their
miſery, and are not comforted, becauſe none from Heaven comes to them:
ſuch as theſe, cannot challenge Chriſt, for not making good his
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, to come to them, if for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly hee have come to them, and they have
ſlighted him. If my Phyſitian, obſerving my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperancy in this or
that, come to me and tell me, unleſſe you refraine ſuch and ſuch
things, you will certainly fall into ſuch and ſuch diſeaſes, which are
ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dangerous; if I ſlight him in <pb n="48" facs="tcp:871:35"/>this, and afterward
fall into thoſe diſeaſes, and lye groaning under them, I cannot blame my
Phyſitian, for not comming to me, but blame my ſelfe that did ſo ſlight
him. So 'tis betweene Chriſt and many a mourning ſoule. Chriſt hath come
to them and told them, that if they go on in this ſinfull courſe and that,
that it will rob them quite of their heavenly comforts; but he in this friendly
way hath beene ſlighted, the ſoule hath beene ſo far taken with the
ſweetneſſe of ſomething below Chriſt, and ſo at laſt hath found
the evill of his owne way, according to Chriſts prediction, and yet
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines of Chriſt not comming to him; but how juſtly, judge you.</p>
            <p>Againe, as this ſoule poſſibly cannot juſtly complaine,
that Chriſt hath not come to him: ſo <pb n="49" facs="tcp:871:35"/>poſſibly hee
cannot juſtly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, that Chriſt is not come to him. That ſoule
which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines after Chriſt, cannot tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay, that Chriſt is not
come to him: for we can never truly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to come to Chriſt, or that
Chriſt ſhould come to us, unleſs he were already with us, and we with
him. Chriſt I conclude then is come to this complaining ſoule, though not
in that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and meaſure as hee deſires him. The thought of that I long
for, if I have the leaſt hope of attaining it, is a degree of
conſolation.</p>
            <p>Finally and more directly, I anſwer to this complaining ſoul
thus, Chriſt as a ſenſible and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory Comforter, comes to us at
his time, and not at ours. Now Chriſts time to come to comfort mourners, is
then, when mourners will make him moſt <pb n="50" facs="tcp:871:36"/>welcome; and that
is uſually when the ſoule is brought to the greateſt extremity, that it
is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of, and not utterly miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry. When <hi>Peter</hi> was ready to
ſink on the Sea, and cryed out, <hi>Maſter ſave mee or I periſh,</hi>
then Chriſt came to him, and catcht him by the hand: thus doth Chriſt
uſually come with ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſatisfactory conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, when
poore ſoules are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt quite ſpent with temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſoule
anguiſh, and look every houre when they ſhall die and drop into Hell.
<hi>He ſhall come to us, as the latter and former raine unto the Earth,</hi>
ſaith the Prophet.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.3.</note> That is, at
the ſeaſonableſt time, when the ſoule will make him moſt welcome; and
that is, when burnt and ſcorcht with Satans fiery darts, as the Earth with
the fervent heat of the Sunne; when parcht and chapt, gaping for 
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:871:36"/>ſome heavenly ſhowers: then Chriſts viſits will be
kindneſſe indeed: and Chriſts conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſweet indeed. This
ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, O mourning ſoul, that Chriſt keeps his word, if he doe
not <hi>leave us comfortleſſe:</hi> and this be aſſured he will not do,
<hi>I will not leave you comfortleſſe, I will come to you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But why wilt thou come to me O my Saviour? To this I anſwer
firſt thus, <hi>viz.</hi> Chriſt will come to his Church Militant to be a
Comforter to fulfill his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers will. <hi>The Spirit of the Lord is upon
me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>becauſe the Lord hath anointed me, to preach
good tydings to the meeke, he hath ſent mee to binde up the broken-hearted,
to proclaime liberty to the Captive, and the opening of Priſon to them that
are bound, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime the acceptable yeare of the Lord, to comfort all that
mourne, <pb n="52" facs="tcp:871:37"/>&amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi>
61.1,2,3.</note> By this Text we ſee, that Chriſt is anointed for this end,
to come to us and be our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, whileſt we live here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low mourning in
<hi>Zion.</hi> What is ſaid of the three friends of <hi>Iob,</hi> that may I
ſay of the bleſſed Trinity. <hi>They made an appointment together, to
come to comfort him.</hi> So the bleſſed Trinity, have made an appointment
together to come to us by Chriſt, and in all diſtreſſes, ſweetly to
comfort us.</p>
            <p>Secondly Chriſt will come as a Comforter to his Church
Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litant, becauſe he hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it. As Chriſt promiſed this in my
Text, ſo in many other Texts. 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 2.11.</note> 
               <hi>And if I goe
away, I will prepare a place for you, and will come againe: and I will pray the
Father, and he ſhall give you ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Comforter, that may abide with you for
ever.</hi> By theſe promiſes <pb n="53" facs="tcp:871:37"/>Chriſt hath obliged
himſelfe, to come as a Comforter to us: let therefore our deſervings of
comfort bee what they will, Chriſt will come to us, becauſe he hath
promiſed he will. Chriſt ſtands much upon his word: Chriſt is God, and
<hi>God cannot lye.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>Though
we beleeve not, yet he abideth faithfull, and cannot deny himſelfe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim</hi> 2</note> A Chriſtian is ready to ſay to
Chriſt as <hi>Iephtha</hi> to the Elders of <hi>Gilead: did not ye
hate me? and expell mee out of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe? and why are ye come to me
now, when yee are in diſtreſſe?</hi> ſaid <hi>Iephtha.</hi> So ſaith
a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, did not I hate thee O my Saviour, and did not I doe what in mee
lay to expell thee from my ſoule, by my ſinning againe and againe againſt
thy Spirit? And why art thou come to mee now, to comfort mee in my
di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe? Why, this that was fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſad, <pb n="54" facs="tcp:871:38"/>ſaid,
may ſuffice, O ſinfull ſoul, as an anſwer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Chriſt looks not at
what thou haſt done, but at what he hath promiſed; and his word he will
keepe, though we change as the Heavens: Heaven and Earth ſhall paſſe
away, but not one jot of his word ſhall fall to the ground. <hi>I will not
leave you comfortleſſe, I will come to you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe I conceive are the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall grounds, why Chriſt comes
as a Comforter to his Church Militant: two grounds more may be alledged, as
<hi>Cauſae minus principales,</hi> leſſe principall cauſes; the firſt
whereof is this, Chriſt comes to us in our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes as a Comforter,
that we may not ſtretch out our hands unto iniquity. Man in diſtreſſe
is ſo deſirous of eaſe, that if Chriſt do not come to him and comfort
him, he'll go to Sin and Satan for eaſe. <hi>Cain</hi> was diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:871:38"/>and becauſe Chriſt did not come to him as a Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
he ran like a vagabond up and downe the world, to finde eaſe in any thing.
<hi>Iudas</hi> was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolate, and becauſe Chriſt as a Comforter did
not come to him, he made a halter his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter. <hi>Saul</hi> being in
diſtreſſe by the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> becauſe Chriſt did not come
to him by Urim, nor by Viſion, nor by Prophets, he went to the Devill for
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. Now that Chriſts children may not thus do, <hi>Chriſt will not
leave them comfortleſſe, but will come to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond ground why Chriſt will come to his Church Militant
as a Comforter, is this, That he may ſtop the mouthes of all ungodly
wretches, who ſay of the godly when in great diſtreſſes,
<hi>Perſecute and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them for there is none to deliver
them,</hi> A <pb n="56" facs="tcp:871:39"/>wicked man looking upon a wounded ſoul with
a carnal eie, breaks cut into ſome ſuch lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage as <hi>Achiſh</hi> did
concerning <hi>David, Loe you ſee the man is mad,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.14.</note> This man is a diſtracted perſon,
fitter for Bedlam, then for Gods houſe: an idle crackt-braine fellow, unfit
to come into ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne aſſemblies. Now that Chriſt may ſilence ſuch
black mouth'd men as theſe, he graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly comes to ſuch wounded
ſoules, and heales their broken hearts, &amp; binds up their wounds; he
powres the Spirit of conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon ſuch as went mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the day
long, and makes them walke with joy and ſtrong conſolation, ſo that
ſuch as cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured them for this and that, are forc'd to lay their hand upon
their mouth, and to condemne themſelves as blinde Bats, and not able to
diſcerne the wayes <pb n="57" facs="tcp:871:39"/>of God towards his children.</p>
            <p>Having thus opened the point in hand, I will in the next place
ſhew you how uſefull it is, to the wicked and to the godly. Will not
Chriſt leave any of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren upon Earth comfortleſſe, but ſtill as
a Comforter come to them? Then you which live in your ſins, and ſo
conſequently none of Chriſts children may collect the unhappineſſe of
your condition from this point. You ſhall live and dye comfortleſſe, for
Chriſt will not come to you as a Comforter; thus he comes only to his
children. Chriſt will not come to you in proſperity as a Comforter; and
therfore in the midſt of ſenſuall laughter, your hearts will be ſad: in
the midſt of all thy worldly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, thy ſpirit will at times gnaw and
beat within thee, and never will all thou enjoyeſt give <pb n="58" facs="tcp:871:40"/>any complacency of comfort to thee, becauſe Chriſt as a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter
comes not to thee. All outward comforts, without the inward conſolations of
Chriſt, they are as good broath unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, which rather cloys then
contents the appetite; they wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, diſtract, and vex, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive the
owner. Be it, that thou art as wiſe as <hi>Achitophel,</hi> as elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent as
<hi>Herod,</hi> as learned as <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> as rich as <hi>Nabal,</hi> as
ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable as <hi>Haman,</hi> as great in the Church as <hi>Iudas;</hi> why,
yet ſhalt thou live comfortleſſe; that is, utterly deſtitute of
Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall conſolation, one droppe whereof hath more ſoule-revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
ſweetneſſe in it, then all the things of this life can afford. Alas! what
is learning? what is wit, wealth, honour, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worldly thing to
comfort me, if Chriſt do not come to me? <pb n="59" facs="tcp:871:40"/>A man may have
all that this world can afford, and yet hang himſelfe for want of comfort, if
Chriſt come not to him, as <hi>Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel, Iudas,</hi> and others have
done.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ob.</hi>
               </note>No men laugh lowder, nor
laugh oftner then wicked men in proſperity: no man merrier in an Alehouſe,
Playhouſe, Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne, Faire, or Market, then they: and are not theſe then
the only comfortable men in this world?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sol.</hi>
               </note>To this I anſwer firſt
thus; laughter is one thing, and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall conſolation another thing.
Every one that laughs hath not a cheerefull ſpirit within: for in the midſt
of laughter a mans heart may be ſad, ſaith <hi>Solomon.</hi> And ſo on
the other hand, every one who hath a comfortable ſpirit, hath not a laughing
face: we do not reade that Chriſt ever <pb n="60" facs="tcp:871:41"/>and yet had more
comfort in his Spirit, then all the merry men of this world.</p>
            <p>Secondly I anſwer thus, ſome mens ſpirits are ſo left of
God to levity and vanity, that they will laugh at the wagging of a ſtraw (as
wee ſay.) This is a great judgement of God upon the ſpirit, and not to be
accounted a comfortable and happy condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? <hi>'Tis a paſtime to fooles to
do wickedly,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon.</hi> This is not properly called
<hi>mirth</hi> (ſaith he) but <hi>madneſſe.</hi> You ſhall ſee mad
men laugh ſometimes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly, and hoope and hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, as if their
ſpirits were as full of joy as they could hold: what ſhall wee conclude
now, that theſe forlorne creatures are in a comfortable condition? Alas!
ſay we, if they were but ſenſible of their condition, they would ſoon
ceaſe laughing, and <pb n="61" facs="tcp:871:41"/>begin lamenting. And ſo may I ſay
to you of all that laugh and rejoyce, and yet live in their ſins, and ſo
conſequently have no Comforter from Heaven come to them, they are mad men:
were their eyes open to ſee their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorne condition, they would quickly
change their note, and turne their mirth into mourning as <hi>Iames</hi>
ſaith.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi>
               </note>Why, but doth not
Chriſt come to the wicked in proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi>
               </note>Yes, no doubt to be made
of of it. Chriſt came to <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> whilſt hee was quaffing in
the golden veſſels of the Temple, and wrote downe his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in
the wall. And thus hee comes to all ungodly perſons in proſperity, to write
downe all their ungodly deeds, that ſo he may exactly judge them at the great
day of account.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:871:42"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi>
               </note>Why, but doth not Chriſt come as a
Comforter, to wicked men that are great and wealthy?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi>
               </note>Chriſt regards no man
for his wealth, or for any externall greatneſſe. If a man be never ſo
rich, or never ſo honourable, yet if hee have not denyed his luſts, and
given up himſelfe to Chriſt, to be ruled by him, Chriſt will never come
to comfort him, if hee would give him all hee hath for his paines; he will not
ſteppe a foot out a doores to a Prince, if he be wicked.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ob.</hi>
               </note>Why, but though hee will not
come to ungodly men as a Comforter in proſperity, when they can make ſome
ſhift with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him, yet hee will come to them as a Comforter in adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
when all other comforters faile.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sol.</hi>
               </note>No hee will not. Chriſt
will not know thy ſoule in adverſity, <pb n="63" facs="tcp:871:42"/>which art a
diſobeyer of him. As he would not let <hi>Dives</hi> have a droppe of water
to coole his tongue, though in unutterable torments, where many oceans would
not in the leaſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure have quenched the flames; ſo neither will hee
afford thee the leaſt drop of conſolation in thy greateſt extremity;
though thou cry Lord, Lord, and cut thy fleſh in the fervency of thy
ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, like <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts to prevaile, yet ſhalt thou be
ſent empty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. Nay Chriſt will be ſo far from being a Comforter to
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly men when in miſery, that hee will adde to their outward miſery,
inward miſery. When thy body is in diſtreſſe, Chriſt will awaken thy
ſoule, that now lyes aſleepe, and ſet thy conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence a gnawing within
thee, which will bee greater torture then if thou wert rackt in every 
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:871:43"/>limbe. Thou maiſt ſend for godly Miniſters &amp;
godly friends to comfort thee then, and they poſſibly may deliver very
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable things, but they ſhall be of no more ſavour to thy ſoule,
then the white of an Egge, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt as a Comforter will not ſpeak
thoſe ſweet things to thy ſoule, which thy friends do to thy eares. As
the Lord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailes the miſerable condition of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> ſo may
I bewaile the miſerable condition of all ungodly men. <hi>Theſe two things
are come unto thee, who ſhall be ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for thee? deſolation and
deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and the famine, and the ſword: by whom ſhall I comfort
thee?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay.</hi> 51.19</note> So ſay I to all
ungodly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, miſery upon miſery will firſt or laſt ſeize upon
you, and who then will be ſorry for you? Famine, and ſword, and
peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; ſickneſſe, and death, and <pb n="65" facs="tcp:871:43"/>judgement;
and by whom will you bee comforted? your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours cannot comfort you: your
riches &amp; friends cannot comfort you: your father the Devill hee will not
then comfort you: your conſcience which you have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſinned againſt,
ſhall not comfort you, but torture you, becauſe Chriſt will not come to
you, to ſprinkle it with his blood, and pacifie it. So that I conclude all
thus: you will live comfortleſſe, dye comfortleſſe, and abide in Hell
after death everlaſtingly comfortleſſe.</p>
            <p>'Tis true all that you ſay Sir: man is a comfortleſſe
Creature indeed, unleſſe Chriſt come to him, I finde it by wofull
experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. I have much wealth in my purſe, and yet but little peace in my
ſpirit. I ſee the Devill (mee thinkes) now &amp; then ſit a ſtride upon
top of my money-bags <pb n="66" facs="tcp:871:44"/>waiting for me, when I come to comfort
my ſelfe in the behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them; and to what this will come at the laſt,
I cannot tell. Sinne I am ſure I do; and comfortleſſe becauſe of
ſinne I am; and more comfortleſſe eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day I look to be, unleſſe
Chriſt come to mee; and yet how to get him to come to me, I know not.</p>
            <p>Would'ſt thou, O comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe creature, have Chriſt to
come to thee? Do then to Chriſt as <hi>Lydia</hi> did to <hi>Paul,</hi>
lovingly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite him to come to thee. Make knowne thy comfortleſſe
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to Chriſt, and then ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly entreat him to viſit thy poore
ſoule. The ground why I exhort thee O ſinner thus to doe, is, becauſe God
hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to give his holy Spirit to them that ask it.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.13.</note> If therefore thou wouldſt have
Chriſt by his <pb n="67" facs="tcp:871:44"/>Spirit to come to thee, invite him, aske
him, beg, and intreat him to come and dwell in thy ſoule; and tell him that
he ſhall have every roome in thy heart at command. As <hi>Rebeckahs</hi>
bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaid to <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſervant, So do thou ſay to Chriſt.
<hi>Come in thou bleſſed of the Lord, wherefore ſtandeſt thou without?
for I have prepared the houſe, and roome for the Camels, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.31</note> Come in thou bleſſed of the Lord,
wherefore ſtandeſt thou without? here is roome for thee and all thy
glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious traine. Here's an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, will, memory, affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they
ſhall be all at thy uſe and ſervice O Chriſt, wherefore come in thou
bleſſed of the Lord, &amp; make thy aboade with me. Thus continue crying to
Chriſt, and longing for him, and by this thou wilt declare thy great love
unto him, and ſo <pb n="68" facs="tcp:871:45"/>make thy ſelfe capable of that ſweet
promiſe, which ſaith, <hi>If a man love mee, the Father loveth him, and wee
will come unto him, and make our aboade with him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.12</note> Then will thy condition bee comfortable
indeed, when thou haſt got ſuch glorious in-mates as theſe to dwell with
thee.</p>
            <p>Having thus ſpoken what I thought fit to the wicked, by way of
application from this point, I will now addreſſe my ſelfe to ſpeake
unto the godly, and ſhew them how uſefull this point may be unto them. I
ſhall firſt ſpeake to ſtrong men, and then unto Babes in Chriſt: to
ſuch as can tell me, that Chriſt as a Comforter is come to them. Secondly
to ſuch as can tell mee they never yet found Chriſt as a Comforter come to
them: and laſtly to ſuch who can tell mee that they have found Chriſt as
a <pb n="69" facs="tcp:871:45"/>Comforter come to them, but now they have loſt him. To
you that tell mee you finde the truth of this doctrine by bleſſed
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that Chriſt is come to you; I have only two things to ſay:
firſt this, Make it ſure to thy ſelfe that Chriſt indeed as a Comforter
is come to thee, and that thy ſoule is not deluded in thy joy &amp;
conſolation. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſtrive ſo to walke, that thy Comforter which is
come to thee may never depart from thee. Firſt ſtrive to make it ſure
that Chriſt is indeed come to thee: that the comfort which thou haſt is
from the Comforter, to wit, the Spirit of Chriſt, and not from the ſpirit
of deluſion.</p>
            <p>There is great need that I ſhould preſſe this inſtruction
up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, becauſe the ſpirit of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion is plentifully powred out in
theſe latter dayes. The hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite <pb n="70" facs="tcp:871:46"/>hath his joy; and he
judges that this his joy, is the joy of the Holy Ghoſt, and as good as need
to bee, whereas it is a joy that ſhall <hi>periſh</hi> (ſaith the
Scripture) a joy that will end in deſperate ſorrow. He thinks that Chriſt
as a Comforter is come to him, whereas 'tis onely the Devill transformed into
an Angell of light. And thus indeed are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands gulled and cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in their comfort. Sadneſſe would overſhadow the ſmiling face of many a
man, if he did but diſcerne how groundleſſe his joy and comfort is; and
what a vaine ſhadow inſtead of a true ſubſtance, his poore ſoule is
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded withall. Wherefore my brethren it concernes you, that tell me, you are
ſenſible that the Comforter is come to you, to take paines to make it
ſure to your ſelves, that your ſoules are not deluded.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:871:46"/>When the Spirit of God came upon <hi>Saul</hi>
that hee propheſied, the people that knew him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid, <hi>What is
come to the Son of Kiſh? is Saul amongſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.11.</note> Thus doe thou ſay to thy ſoul
who art ſo merry and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, <hi>viz.</hi> What is come to thee O my
ſoule! that thou art now ſo joyfull and cheerefull? Once I am ſure thou
went'ſt mourning all the day long: is Chriſt as a Comforter come to thee?
If Chriſt by his Spirit have brought glad tydings to thee, why then O my
glory, continue in thy mirth: but if not, why art thou ſo merry O my ſoule?
thy mirth is but madneſſe. As <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> queſtioned his ſoule for
ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſaying, <hi>Why art thou ſo ſad O my ſoule? and why
art thou ſo caſt downe within me?</hi> So maiſt thou doe well to
queſtion thy mirth, ſaying, why art thou ſo merry <pb n="72" facs="tcp:871:47"/>O
my ſoule? and why art thou ſo much lifted up within me? Is thy Comforter
our Lord Jeſus Chriſt indeed come to thee? O then my glory ceaſe not to
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare thy comfort, by any come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poſture and geſture: but if not, a
houſe of mourning, O my ſoule, is fitter for thee then a houſe of mirth;
garments of Sackcloth and ſadneſſe, would better become thee, then
gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of joy and gladneſſe. You know how <hi>Iſaac</hi> once ſpake
to his ſonne, <hi>Art thou</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>my very Sonne
Eſau?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.24</note> So doe thou humbly
queſtion thy Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Art thou my very Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter indeed? Art thou the
<hi>very Chriſt</hi> the Sonne of God, which ſpeakeſt conſolation to my
ſoul? You know how <hi>Iohn</hi> queſtioned Chriſt much after this
manner, that hee might not be deceived concerning him. 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.3</note>
               <hi>Art thou he that 
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:871:47"/>ſhould come, or do wee not looke for another?</hi> So do
thou ſay, Art thou hee that ſhould come and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort my ſoule? or
ſhould not I look for another? There be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny falſe Chriſts, and falſe
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forters now in the world, and they deceive many: wherefore I beſeech thee
ſpeak out, and ſpeak plainly to my ſoule, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou bee hee that
ſhould come and comfort mee yea or not, that if I have obtained the true
Comforter, I may give God the glory of his great kindneſſe; if not, I may
ſeeke out for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>How ſhould I know (may the ſtrong man in Chriſt ſay to me)
whether hee that is come to my ſoule with conſolation, bee hee that
ſhould come, or not? How ſhould I be able to make it ſure to my ſoule,
that the conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which I have is from the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit <pb n="74" facs="tcp:871:48"/>of
Chriſt, and not from a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of deluſion?</p>
            <p>To this I thus anſwer, <hi>viz.</hi> If he that is come to thy
ſoule bee hee that ſhould come, to wit, Chriſt; thou ſhalt finde that
hee doth more workes then one in thy ſoule: he doth not only com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort thee,
but hee doth many great works beſides this. Chriſt doth many great workes
in a mans ſoule before he comforts him; and hee doth many great workes in his
ſoul, after he hath comforted him. Chriſt doth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great workes in the
ſoule of man, before he comforts him: he doth break the heart before he
bindes it up: he firſt wounds the heart, before he will heale it: he caſts
downe the ſoule for ſinne, before he will raiſe it up. Now to break the
heart of man, which the Scripture compares to an <hi>Adamant</hi> for
hardneſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zech.</hi> 7.12.</note> is 
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:871:48"/>a great work; and yet this doth Chriſt throughly, before
hee comforts throughly. The break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the hard heart of man, hath many great
works about it, ere it be effected. The convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the ſoule of ſinne,
which ſelfe-conceited man is not eaſily brought unto. The making of ſin
out of meaſure ſinfull, in the ſoules apprehenſion, which blinde man is
not eaſily brought to ſee. The making of man to loathe himſelfe, for the
evils which hee hath committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, which man full of ſelfe-love
is not eaſily wrought unto. The making of man to long for peace and
reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God, as the greateſt happineſſe in the world, and to
beg this bleſſing with teares, as a ſoule that ſees hee ſhall dye and
periſh eternally without it; which man that naturally hates 
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:871:49"/>God, is not eaſily wonne unto. Yet all theſe difficult
workes doth Chriſt doe in the ſoule of man, before he comes as a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter
to him. Which Chriſt confirmes where he ſaith, <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are they
that mourne, for they ſhall be comforted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now would'ſt thou know whether he that is come to thy ſoule,
bee hee that ſhould come or not? why then tell me, What did precede thy
comfort which now thou haſt? Did Chriſt leade thee to the Wels of
Conſolation by the waters of <hi>Marah?</hi> Did hee bring thee to ſowe in
teares, ere he gave thee to reape thy great harveſt of joy? Waſt thou ever
in the houſe of mourning? Did the ſpirit of heavineſſe for ſin ever
take hold on thee? Was thy hard heart firſt broken, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this bound up?
Firſt woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <pb n="77" facs="tcp:871:49"/>and after this healed? Didſt thou goe
mourning for diſhonouring God all the day long, and after many dolorous dayes
thus ſpent, did thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter come to thee? Surely then he that is come, is
he that ſhould come, and do not looke for another: but if otherwiſe, thou
haſt juſt cauſe to bee jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of thy joy.</p>
            <p>Againe, Chriſt as hee doth great workes in the ſoule before he
comforts it, ſo he doth great workes in the ſoule after hee hath comforted
it. That ſoule which Chriſt comforts, he makes a very fruitfull ſoule in
all grace to his glory. No waters make the ſoule of a Chriſtian grow in
grace, like the waters of conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. The comforting Spirit of Chriſt is
to a Chriſtian in the wayes of obedience, as winde and tide to a Ship: that
which <pb n="78" facs="tcp:871:50"/>makes him runne the wayes of Gods Commandements. That
Chriſtian which is comforted by Chriſt, prayes fervently, and prayes
frequently. Conſolation gives winges to ſupplication. That Chriſtian
which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted by Chriſt, prayſeth God with ſtrong affection. A
ſoule comforted by Chriſt, is as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument well tuned by a skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
Muſitian: hee will, upon every occaſion, make ſweet me lody in the eares
of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. True conſolation is from Heaven, and it carries that
ſoule ſtrongly to Heaven, in which it is. True conſolation is from
Chriſt, and it will make a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian live wholly to Chriſt. To whom much
is forgiven they love much: and this love con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraines them to deny
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to follow Chriſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:871:50"/>Would'ſt thou know then for certaine O
ſtrong man in Chriſt, that hee which is come to thy ſoule, is he which
ſhould come? Why then look what activity is in thy ſoule to duty. Is thy
ſoule as a Gyant refreſhed after wine? ſtrong and vigorous to the
pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of all good duties? Art thou abundant in the worke of the Lord? Art
thou a ſweet Singer in Iſrael of the prayſes of the Lord? Is thy heart at
thy mouth leaping within thee, like the Babe in <hi>Elizabeths</hi> wombe when
thou art telling what God hath done for thy ſoule? Art thou (in a word) a
holy &amp; heavenly man, as one comforted by a holy and heavenly God? Doth thy
joy tranſcend the joyes that this world affords, in ſweetneſſe? Doth it
raiſe thy ſpirit to admire the love of God? and doth it make thee dead to
ſecular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights? <pb n="80" facs="tcp:871:51"/>and to account naked carnall mirth
madneſſe? empty huskes for brutes to feed on? Then mayeſt thou
comfortably conclude, that he which is come to thy ſoule, is he which
ſhould come, and do not look for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: but if thou art merry and
cheerfull, but not holy and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly, hee that is come to thy ſoul, is not
he that ſhould come, wherefore I beſeech thee to look for another.</p>
            <p>A ſecond inſtruction which I would commend to ſtrong men in
Chriſt is this: after thou haſt made it ſure to thy ſoule, that
Chriſt as a Comforter is indeed come to thee, then ſtrive ſo to walke,
that he may never depart from thee. So a man may walk, that Chriſt as a
Comforter may forſake his ſoule. <hi>David</hi> had wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full experience of
this truth, and ſo doubtleſſe have many elſe of <pb n="81" facs="tcp:871:51"/>the
godly. So a man may walke that Chriſt as a Comforter never depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him.
But how ſhould I thus walk, ſaith the comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſoule, that I might
enjoy this heaven below, till I come to that above, and ſo go from joy to
joy; from joy unſpeakable and full of glory, to joy that cannot enter into
any mortall heart to conceive of?</p>
            <p>To this I thus anſwer, Do not grieve Chriſt that is come to
thee: Secondly, do all that thou canſt to delight him, if thou would'ſt
have him continually abide with thee. Doe not ſit downe and reſt, as one
that hath a licence to be lazie, and as if all thy work were done, now thy
Comforter is come to thee; this will grieve him, and quickly make him leave
thee. Thou haſt obtained Chriſt to come a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter to thee, well: yet let
mee <pb n="82" facs="tcp:871:52"/>tell thee as <hi>Moſes</hi> did the
<hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, You are not</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>as yet come to the reſt,
and to the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance which the Lord your God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth you.</hi> So ſay I to
thee O com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted ſoule, thou art not yet come to thoſe degrees of
conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, which thou mayeſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine unto in this life, if thou
continue to be thrifty. The joy of the Holy Ghoſt is a bottome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
Well, which thou canſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver draw dry: and the more thou draweſt, the
freſher and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſtill ſhalt thou finde it. The joy of the Holy
Ghoſt is no ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feting thing, as ſome earthly ſweets are: and therefore
thou mayeſt ſafely ſay, <hi>Lord ever more give me of this bread:</hi>
fill my ſoule with Flagons of this precious liquour: let thy love bee ſhead
abroad in my heart by the Holy Ghoſt: let my ſoule delight her ſelfe in
this fatneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:871:52"/>Secondly, now Chriſt as a Comforter is come
to thee, doe not wax wanton againſt him, this alſo will grieve him, and
make him quickly forſake thy ſoule as a Comforter Let all the
manifeſtations of thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort be ſuitable to thy Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; holy as he is
holy; ſpirituall and heavenly, as he is. <hi>When yee are come into the good
land, take heed that ye doe not forget the Lord</hi> (ſaid <hi>Moſes</hi>
to <hi>Iſrael.</hi>) So ſay I to you that finde Chriſt with you as a
Comforter, which are come to the fellowſhip of the Spirit, and to the
participation of that tranſcendant comfort which is by him: take heed that
you grow not giddy headed, and forget God and your ſelves. The waters of
conſolation are ſtrong waters, and mans weake head and heart cannot beare
much of them ſteadily, but are ready to <pb n="84" facs="tcp:871:53"/>reele to one
ſide or other. When the clouds of heaven have well watered the Earth, then
doe weeds as well as good hearbes ſpring apace: ſo when Chriſt by his
Spirit, ſweetly waters the ſoul w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> conſolation, then levity and
vanity, as well as Chriſtian mirth and cheerfulneſſe ſpring amaine; If
a Chriſtian bee not very watchfull over his ſoule, to pluck up ſuch
weedes by the rootes, as ſoone as they begin to ſhew themſelves. I
conclude this thus: thou that art comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Spirit, let not the
ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtations of thy comfort grieve the Spirit. This remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that Satan
hath an art to bring evill out of the greateſt good, as God hath an art to
bring good out of the greateſt evill: and therefore beg that thou mayeſt
not be ignorant of any of his devices, nor unable <pb n="85" facs="tcp:871:53"/>to
reſiſt them, if thou would'ſt not looſe thy Comforter.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if thou would'ſt have thy Comforter to abide ſtill
with thee; as thou muſt not grieve him, ſo thou muſt doe all that thou
canſt to delight him. Let it be thy meat and drink to follow all the motions
of the Spirit of Chriſt: whitherſoever Chriſt would have thee go, or
whatſoever Chriſt would have thee do, cheerefully obey him; this will
delight thy Comforter exceedingly, and make him to rejoyce to continue with
thee. If Chriſt ſay unto thee as to the Fiſhermen, <hi>Follow
me:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 4 19.</note> do thou readily reply as
the Scribe, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, I will follow thee whitherſoever thou
goeſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 8 19.</note> This is to declare
the genuine diſpoſition of Chriſts people, which Chriſt is exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly
taken withall. Chriſts people are a willing people in <pb n="86" facs="tcp:871:54"/>their obedience, <hi>Thy people ſhall be willing in the day of thy
power, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110 3</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Humbly and compaſſionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tell diſconſolate
ſoules, what Chriſt hath done for thy ſoule: this will delight thy
Comforter much, and make him rejoyce to continue with thee. Chriſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights
to ſee his children com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municative of the ſweet meates which hee gives
them. And therefore as <hi>Iael</hi> ſaid to <hi>Barak,</hi> ſo do thou O
comforted ſoule, to ſuch as yet go mourning all the day long: <hi>Come</hi>
(ſaid ſhe) <hi>and I will ſhew thee the man whom thou
ſeekeſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 4.22.</note> Come O ſad
ſoule, that canſt not finde him whom thy ſoule loveth, I will ſhew thee
the man whom thou ſeekeſt; the manner of his comming to my poore ſoule;
and how long hee made me waite upon him, ere he would come to me; and how 
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:871:54"/>well hee hath now made mee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends for all his ſtaying.
And therfore <hi>Although thou ſayeſt thou ſhalt not ſee him, yet
judgement is before him, therefore truſt thou in him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 35.14.</note> 
               <hi>For the viſion is yet for an
ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time, but at the end it ſhall ſpeak and not lye: though it
tarry, wait for it, becauſe it will ſurely come, it will not
tarry.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.3.</note> The more imparting of
experiments of love wee are, to the glory of Chriſt, the more ſtill will
Chriſt graciouſly give us to our further comfort. And this indeed is Gods
end in comforting ſome of his children, <hi>that they may bee able to comfort
them which are in any trouble, by the comfort where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they themſelves are
comforted of God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.4.</note> as the
Apoſtle ſweetly affirmes.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Thank Chriſt humbly and heartily for his comming to
thee; if thou would<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt have him 
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:871:55"/>abide ſtill with thee. The Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites when they came
into the promiſed Land which flowed with milk and honey, they were to take
the firſt of all the fruits of the Earth, and put them in a basket, and ſo
preſent them to the Prieſt ſaying, viz. <hi>And now behold, I have
brought the firſt fruits of the Land, which thou the Lord haſt given
me:</hi> thus were they to ſet their firſt fruits before the Lord, and to
worſhip before him, as you may ſee at large.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.</note> Why you that enjoy Chriſt as a
Comforter, you have received the firſt fruits of that good land, which
<hi>Canaan</hi> typified, which flowes with Milke and Honey. Bring therefore
theſe firſt fruits, and ſet them before God and worſhip: bring the
ſweet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of the Holy Ghoſt in your hearts, before the Lord and
ſay, Behold ô Chriſt, theſe and theſe <pb n="89" facs="tcp:871:55"/>are the
ſweet conſolations of thy ſpirit: and loe for them all I humbly render
praiſe to thy name. Such mighty enemies of my peace, haſt thou conquered:
ſuch doubts which ſo long trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled me, haſt thou anſwered: ſuch
wants which ſo long time kept mee exceeding low, haſt thou ſupplyed: to
thee O God be the glory of thine own good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>You have great cauſe thus to magnifie the Lord for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
which finde Chriſt as a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter come to you. You enjoy that bleſſing
which exceedeth all outward bleſſings. The light of Gods countenance lifted
up, upon a poore mourning ſoule, 'tis of farre greater value then Corne,
Wine, Oyle; then Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, Rubies, or any choice thing that this world can
afford. The naked revelation of Chriſt in the <pb n="90" facs="tcp:871:56"/>ſoule of
man, is of more worth then all theſe, ſaith <hi>Solomon:</hi> the moſt
glorious revelation of Chriſt then to the ſoule, which the ſoule of man
is capable of in this life, muſt needs be of much more tranſcendant worth.
You enjoy that bleſſing which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth many inward bleſſings. It
exceedeth knowledge: for what is knowledge in the head, to the joy of the Holy
Ghoſt in the heart? One beame of light in the underſtanding, is of more
worth then all the Silver and Gold, Gemmes, and Jewels in the world; and yet
one beame of the light of Gods counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, ſhining upon the heart, though
but by reflexion from the face of Jeſus Chriſt, is of more worth then all
knowledge which humane ſtudy can at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine unto. I cannot ſay that this
bleſſing, exceedeth the leaſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <pb n="91" facs="tcp:871:56"/>grace in the
ſoule: but this I can ſafely ſay, that conſolation 'tis the gloſſe
and glory of every grace: every grace ſhines in its full luſtre where the
Comforter dwels. This I can further ſay, that you enjoy that bleſſing
which makes Heaven a Heaven, and which makes Earth a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to you: and
therefore you have great reaſon to magnifie the Lord for his mercy. The more
of Heaven we enjoy upon Earth, the more ſhould we ſet our ſelves to doe
the worke of them which are in Heaven, whileſt on Earth.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Finally let Chriſts mediate comming to thee by his
Spirit, make thee long earneſtly for his immediate comming to thee in his
owne perſon: this delights Chriſt, that his Spouſe ſhould ſay,
<hi>Come,</hi> as the Spirit doth.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.17</note>
That ſhee ſhould long for the <pb n="92" facs="tcp:871:57"/>wedding day, as he doth.
When good old <hi>Simeon</hi> had imbraced the conſolation of Iſrael, for
which hee ſo long waited, hee then deſired preſently to be
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved: ſo thou that haſt imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the conſolation of Iſrael,
ſhould'ſt in a holy manner with <hi>Simeon, Iob,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi>
deſire to bee diſſolved and to bee with Chriſt which is beſt of all.
You whom Chriſt hath kiſſed with the kiſſes of his lips, ſhould
long earneſtly to lye betweene his breaſts all night; my meaning is, to
have a full enjoyment of Chriſt. Thus have I done ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſuch, who
can tell me that Chriſt as a Comforter is come to them.</p>
            <p>In the next place I addreſſe my ſelfe to ſpeak to ſuch
of the godly, who can tell me that they never yet found Chriſt as a Comforter
come to them. Two <pb n="93" facs="tcp:871:57"/>or three things I have to ſay to you
from this ſweet doctrine. 
<note place="margin">1.</note>Firſt, I would have you to labour to
beleeve this doctrine, that Chriſt <hi>will not leave you comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,
but will certainly</hi> (at laſt) <hi>come to you.</hi> Chriſt hath
repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his promiſe, which is as a bond with many ſeales; and therefore
thou haſt juſt ground to beleeve, ô comfortleſſe ſoule, that
Chriſt <hi>will not leave thee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe, but will come to
thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Object.</hi>
               </note>What juſt ground have
I to beleeve, that Chriſt will come to me, ſeeing he is holy, and I am
unholy: hee is glorious in holineſſe, and I am abominable in ſin and
wickedneſſe, ſaith the weake comfortleſſe ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sol.</hi>
               </note>Art thou more vile then
<hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſeh?</hi> Chriſt came to him and comforted him. Art thou more
muddie and earthy then <hi>Zache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us?</hi> Chriſt came to him and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted 
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:871:58"/>him. Art thou more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veliſh then <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi>
out of whom were caſt ſeven Devils? Chriſt came to her, and filled her
ſoule with ſtrong conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Why ſhould'ſt not thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, that
Chriſt will come to thee too, and quiet and comfort thy mourning
ſpirit?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sol.</hi>
               </note>But ſecondly I anſwer
thus: <hi>viz.</hi> Chriſt doth not ſo much lock how thou art qualified, as
at what hee hath promiſed: Chriſt hath promiſed hee will come to thee,
and he is faithfull and will doe it. If thy ſoule were never ſo poore,
never ſo blinde, never ſo wretched, never ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, yet Chriſt having
promiſed to come to thee, hee will make good his word; though he come
backward, with a mantle to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thy nakedneſie, as <hi>Shem</hi> and
<hi>Iaphet</hi> did to <hi>Noah.</hi> If thy ſoule were full of wounds; if
thy ſoule <pb n="95" facs="tcp:871:58"/>were full of running putrifying ſores; if
thou wert as black with ſin as an <hi>Ethiopian;</hi> if thou wert as
ſpotted with ſin as a Leopard; nay, if thy ſoule did ſtink with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
thee, as <hi>Lazarus</hi> body after ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of the Earth againe, yet
Chriſt having promiſed to come to thee and comfort thee, he will doe it,
though he hold his noſe while hee bee comforting thy ſtinking naſty
ſoule. Heaven and Earth ſhall paſſe away, but not a jot or tittle of
Chriſts pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe ſhall faile. <hi>The voice of my Beloved, behold he
commeth leaping upon the Mountaines, and skipping upon the Hils.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.8.</note> Though there bee mountaines and hils of
ſin in thy ſoule, yet Chriſt will come skip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping over all theſe with
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to thy ſoule, rather then thou ſhalt be left comfortleſſe.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, O weake, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe ſoule, ſay not of thy
Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour <pb n="96" facs="tcp:871:59"/>and Comforter as <hi>Balaam</hi> did, <hi>I
ſhall ſee him, but not now; I ſhall behold him, but not nigh.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 24.17.</note> I ſhall ſee Chriſt come with a
wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: nay with many thouſand witneſſes, at the great day, when
<hi>every eye ſhall ſee him:</hi> but I ſhall not ſee him come to me
now, in this ſoule dolour, as a Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. I ſhall behold him
perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, as <hi>Moſes</hi> beheld the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Land, afar off: he will
never come nigh my poore ſoule, to ſtay it with thoſe comforts w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> it
needs. Ceaſe, O weak ſoule, this incredulous language; and ſtrive to
beleeve, and this ſweet promiſe I treat of ſhall be made good unto thee.
No ſinne ſo mighty to keepe thy Comforter from thee, as unbeliefe. Say then
O mourning Chriſtian to thy comfortleſſe ſoule. <hi>Yet a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
while, and he that ſhall come will come, and will not tarry.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.37</note> He that <pb n="97" facs="tcp:871:59"/>hath ſaid
he will come as a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter to thee, will come, and will ſatisfie thy
ſoule with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, as with marrow and fatneſſe. Say to thy ſad
ſoule, with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>My God will come, and will not keepe
ſilence:</hi> he will ſpeak conſolation ſo plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that my ignorant
ſoule ſhall underſtand; ſo powerfully, that my incredulous ſoule
ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, and owne her own mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. Thou art now toſſed and
almoſt drowned, O my ſoule, with reſtleſſe waves of miſery; but the
Spirit will move upon theſe waters; thou ſhalt ſee Chriſt comming
towards thee, upon theſe troubleſome waves anon, and ſay, <hi>be not
afraid, it is I:</hi> I that have loved thee, and given my ſelfe for thee,
and none ſhall pluck thee out of my hand.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as I would have <pb n="98" facs="tcp:871:60"/>thee to ſtrive
firmely to beleeve this truth, ſo I would have thee endeavour patiently to
waite the accompliſhment of it. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that Chriſt will come to thee, and
waite patiently untill hee doe come. There is good ground why every ſoule
ſhould patiently waite for Chriſt, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to him, whither we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
our ſelves which are to bee viſited, or Chriſt our viſitour. If thou O
comfortleſſe ſoule con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider thy ſelfe which art to bee viſited,
there is great reaſon thou ſhould'ſt waite patiently till Chriſt come
to thee, how long ſoever he ſtay. Firſt, thou art a creature, and
Chriſt is thy Creator; and ſhould not a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture wait on his Creator? Thou
art a ſervant, and Chriſt is thy Lord: and ſhould not a ſervant waite
on his Lord? Conſider thee in thy higheſt relations, and 
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:871:60"/>they all call for waiting. Thou art a Sonne, and Chriſt
is thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and ſhould not a Sonne wait on his Father? Thou art a Wife,
and Chriſt is thy Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band: and ſhould not a Wife wait on her
Huſband?</p>
            <p>Secondly, conſider that thou haſt deſerved, that Chriſt
ſhould never come to thee, and yet for
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll this, ſeeing hee will come to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hee, haſt not thou juſt cauſe
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o wait patiently till hee doe come,
how long ſo ever it bee firſt? Before thy calling thou didſt reject
Chriſt; and ſince <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hy calling,
thou haſt often grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Chriſt; and haſt not thou
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen deſerved that Chriſt
ſhould never come to thee? Thou haſt quenched many a ſweet motion of the
Spirit of Chriſt: thou haſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urned the deafe eare, to the ſweet ſtill voice that hath
ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken behinde thee, times with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <pb n="100" facs="tcp:871:61"/>out number, and
ſo ſlighted the Spirit of Chriſt; and haſt not thou then juſtly
deſerved, that Chriſt as a Comforter ſhould never come to thee? yet
ſeeing he will come, for all this unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; haſt not thou juſt
cauſe to wait patiently for him, how long ſoever he ſtay? Thou haſt
many weekes, many moneths, nay many yeeres, gone along in a courſe of
grieving Chriſt; and doeſt thou think much of wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a few weeks, a few
moneths, a few yeeres, for Chriſt to come to comfort thee?</p>
            <p>Take this in another forme: thou didſt make Chriſt wait a long
time upon thee, ere thou wouldſt let him abide with thee as a ſpirit of
reformation: and is there not juſt cauſe then, that thou ſhouldſt wait
patiently a long time upon him, if he will have it ſo, ere hee abide with 
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:871:61"/>thee as a Spirit of conſolation? how many knocks did
Chriſt give at thy ſtubborne heart, ere thou wouldſt open to him? how
much dew of the night diſtilled upon his locks, ere thou wouldſt give him
houſe roome in thy heart? how many mercies? how many corrections, were all
ſpilt upon thee, ere Chriſt could win thee to reſpect him? canſt thou
tell? if thou canſt not, think not much, if Chriſt make thee ſhed a few
teares, and breathe out a few groanes, ere he bring glad tydings of peace unto
thee.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if thou conſider Chriſt thy viſitour, there is all
the reaſon that can be, that thou ſhouldſt wait patiently, till hee come
to thee. Chriſt will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly come to thee: Chriſt will come to thee at
the fitteſt time: Chriſt will come richly when he doth come; which are all
ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <pb n="102" facs="tcp:871:62"/>grounds of patience. Chriſt will certainly
come to thee, O comfortleſſe ſoule, though it may ſeeme to thee,
ſomething long firſt. Thou doeſt not wait for one that will not come at
all, as the <hi>Turk</hi> waiteth for <hi>Mahomet:</hi> nay, thou doeſt not
wait for one that will frivolouſly delay the time of his comming. Thou
doeſt not wait for one that will deceive thee. Chriſt hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to
come to thee, and he is faithfull, and cannot deny him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. There is two
things in faithfulneſſe: firſt, that a man ſhould own what he hath
ſaid; &amp; then ſecondly, that he ſhould make it good. Now both theſe
will Chriſt do: Chriſt will not eat his words, as we ſay: what he hath
promiſed he will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, and will make good; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever labour or
loſſe he be at to do it. Chriſt is not mutable as <pb n="103" facs="tcp:871:62"/>we
are, to promiſe one thing to day, and recall it againe to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row: <hi>he is
immutable and changeth not, therfore we are not conſumed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou doeſt not wait for one that will frivolouſly delay the
time of his comming. Chriſt will not deale with thy comfortleſſe ſoule,
as thoſe ſorry gheſts dealt with Chriſt, make excuſes: one had bought
a yoke of Oxen, and therefore could not come: an other a Farm, &amp;c. Chriſt
will not tell thee, as <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Dives</hi> in hell, between thy ſoul &amp;
him is a great gulfe, ſo that there can be no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſe between them.
Nor, that from Heaven to Earth, is too long a journey for him to make: He will
not tell thee, that the place where thy ſick com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe ſoule lyes,
is filthy, and altogether unfit for him to come to. Hee will not tell thee that
thy ſoule is ſo far gone in griefe <pb n="104" facs="tcp:871:63"/>and deſperate
ſorrow, that 'tis in vain for him to come to thee. Chriſt puts none of
theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes upon any of his patients.</p>
            <p>No, the ground why Chriſt ſtayes is, that hee may come at the
fitteſt time; and then he will come with healing in his wings, if all the
Devils in Hell ſhould oppoſe him, which me thinks ſhould be a
ſatisfactory ground of patience, to any diſconſolate ſoule. If a
Phyſitian yet apply this and that for further evacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, rather then
cordials, as knowing the body not yet fit for cordials, will not any wiſe man
ſubmit patiently to his way? ſo if Chriſt for bear giving thy ſick
ſoule cordials, as hee that well knowes thy ſoule not fit yet, for ſuch
luſcious things, wilt not thou with much thankfulneſſe acknowledge his
great care over thy ſoule, and with all patience <pb n="105" facs="tcp:871:63"/>waite
his leaſure? I patiently undergoe the paine of drawing plaiſters, when I
know my ſore is not fit for healing: thus ſhould it be in ſpirituall
diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: wee ſhould patiently un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe griefe and ſorrow,
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till our ſoules bee fit for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, and then we ſhall bee ſure
to have it.</p>
            <p>Finally, bee ſure of this, O mourning ſoule, that Chriſt
will come richly, when hee doth come; and therefore methinkes thou
ſhould'ſt waite patiently for him: what Merchant but would waite patiently,
the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turne of his Ship in the longeſt voiage, if hee were ſure that it
would richly returne at laſt, Chriſt will come very richly furniſhed,
with the comforts of the Holy Ghoſt, which are unſpeakable and glorious, to
your ſoules that mourne after <pb n="106" facs="tcp:871:64"/>him, and waite for him.
What the Apoſtle once ſpake of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in relation to the
<hi>Romans,</hi> that may I truely ſay of Chriſt, in relation to all that
mourne after him <hi>And I am ſure that when I come unto you, I ſhall
come</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in the fulneſſe of the bleſſing of the
Goſpell of Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom</hi> 15.29.</note>
Chriſt I am ſure O mourning ſoule, when he doth come unto thee, hee wilt
come in the fulneſſe of the bleſſing of the Holy Ghoſt: thou ſhalt
have joy in the Holy Ghoſt unſpeakable and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Thou by long waiting
art made a more vaſt Veſſell, to hold the precious waters of
conſolation; and Chriſt by long ſtaying doth (as I may ſay) the more
furniſh himſelfe, with theſe waters of life, to refreſh, fill, and
ſatiſfy thy thirſty ſoule, when he comes to thee. Chriſt will heale
throughly thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <pb n="107" facs="tcp:871:64"/>heart, and binde up all thy woundes:
he will anſwer all thy doubts, and cleare all thy ſcruples: hee will quiet
thy quarrelling conſcience, and ſtill thy complaining Spirit: he will fill
thy ſadde ſoule with joy and gladneſſe, and thy dejected ſpirit with
Songs of thankes gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</p>
            <p>If theſe things, O mourning ſoule, will not make thee waite
patiently, till thy Comforter come to thee, but thou wilt murmure and repine,
and fall upon indirect wayes to get con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, know that by this practice
thou wilt make thy condition more miſerable, then at preſent it is. Thou
wilt grieve him that ſhould come as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter to thee: and if thou by
ſinne make Chriſt grieve, how can Chriſt by his Spirit make thee rejoyce?
and if thou ſet <pb n="108" facs="tcp:871:65"/>him a mourning that can onely comfort
thee, by whom wilt thou bee comforted? Doſt thou thinke to winne Chriſt to
thee, by a dogged diſpoſition? Chriſt may pitty, and cure thy hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours,
but t'will never bee by conſolation. He will bring thee to bee lowly and
meeke ere thou ſhalt find reſt to thy ſoule; hee will make thee willing
to lye under his Feete; glad of crummes of comfort; and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to waite for
them till Chriſt hath dined, and every Child ſerved.</p>
            <p>If thy corrupt ſoule hanker after the pleaſure of ſinne
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, becauſe Chriſt as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter doth not come to thee, and thou bee
reſolved to picke and chuſe, amongſt all the ſins thy ſoule knowes,
to finde out one that thy ſoule moſt loves, to make a comforter to thee, as
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:871:65"/>the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in their dogged hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour made
them a Captaine to returne to <hi>Aegypt</hi> againe, know this, that what
ſinne thou pitcheſt upon to make a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, that ſinne will Chriſt
make a Divell to torture thee: Chriſt will make thee know by woefull
experience that the ſweeteſt ſinne, is a bitter and miſerable
comforter: that the leaſt ſinne, is too great an evill, truly to comfort
the ſoule: that to goe to the Divell for conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, is to make faſter
haſt for comfort, then good ſpeed: that neither ſinne, nor any thing in
the world beſide ſin ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort thy ſoule, when he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe will
not.</p>
            <p>The laſt Inſtruction that I have to commend to thee, O
comfortleſſe ſoule, that did'ſt never yet finde Chriſt as a
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter come to thee, is this, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve <pb n="110" facs="tcp:871:66"/>how Chriſt
comes, and do not put him off. Chriſt comes to comfortleſſe ſoules with
comfort, in a promiſe; as I have at large ſhewed you.<note place="margin">Tis
with many Chriſtians in their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nority, as twas with <hi>Samuel,</hi>
the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> doe not know the voyce of the
Lord, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n a promiſe,
&amp; therefore I thought good to note this laſt inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> The
promiſe Chriſt opens before the ſoule, that hee may ſee the
bleſſing wrapt up in it, which he needes: and then often repeates it to the
ſoule, that he may rely upon it: inſtances to illuſtrate this way of
Chriſt, I have given you, things muſt not bee here againe repeated. That
which here I would preſſe by way of application, is, that you which are
comfortleſſe ſoules, would obſerve this ſecret way of the comforter,
and meet him. Art thou tempted? and doſt thou now heare a ſweet ſtill
voyce, as it were behind thee ſaying, <hi>My grace ſhall bee ſufficient
for thee?</hi> Why this is the voyce of thy beloved, that is come to 
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:871:66"/>thee, embrace what hee ſaith, reſt upon it, turne not
thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter away now, by unbeliefe, and peeviſh pettiſh humours. Haſt
thou fallen into ſinne, by the ſtrength of temptation, and thine owne
corruption? and doſt thou heare ſuch a ſweete voyce behind thee as this,
<hi>The bloud of Ieſus Chriſt cleanſeth us from all ſinne?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh</hi> 1.7.</note> Why this is the language of thy
beloved, hee is come to comfort thee, O mourning ſoule, doe not thruſt him
away by unkinde language of unbeliefe and paſſion. Heare what he ſaith,
for it is ſweete: ſtrive to believe what he ſaith, for it is ſure. As
<hi>Iſaac</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Jacob</hi> his Sonne, after hee had had ſome
diſcourſe at a diſtance with him, <hi>Come neere now and kiſſe mee my
Sonne:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.26.</note> So ſhould ſuch
comfortleſſe ſoules ſay to Chriſt, when they heare Chriſt 
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:871:67"/>ſpeaking, as it were at a diſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, ſoftly and
coldly to them, the ſweet promiſes of his word; come heere now, O my
belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and kiſſe mee with theſe kiſſes of thy lippes for thy love
is better then Wine: what thou ſayeſt to my ſoule, ſay it with ſuch
life, that my heart may no longer be faithleſſe, but believe, and give
glory to thee. I have now done ſpeaking to you, who never yet had the
comforter come to you.</p>
            <p>I come now in the laſt place to ſpeake a word or two
par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, to ſuch of GODS people, who can tell mee that they have found
Chriſt as a comforter come to them, but now have loſt Him. Three things I
have to ſay to theſe. Firſt, labour to bee ſenſible of thy loſſe.
Secondly, blame not Chriſt for departing from thee. <pb n="113" facs="tcp:871:67"/>Thirdly, uſe all holy meanes to get him to returne to thee againe.
Firſt I would have thee, O deſerted ſoule, to labour to bee truly
ſenſible of thy loſſe Though it bee that ſome are deeply ſenſible
of this great loſſe, yet others are as deeply ſtupid, which moves mee to
note this inſtruction. For a man to bee ſtupid and ſenſeleſſe
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der corporall afflictions, argues a very ill temper of ſpirit; but for a
man to bee ſtupid and ſenſeleſſe under ſpirituall affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
under ſuch a ſpirituall affliction as this, the loſſe of the Sunne, the
loſſe of Chriſt as a comforter, argues a very ill temper of ſpirit
indeed. Strive therefore, O deſerted ſtupid ſoule, to affect thine heart
throughly with thy loſſe. Thou haſt loſt more then <hi>Iob:</hi> when
hee had loſt Children; <pb n="114" facs="tcp:871:68"/>ſubſtance, health, honours,
and friends: nay thou haſt loſt more, then if thou hadſt loſt this
World; nay, thou haſt loſt more then if thou hadſt loſt thy life, which
is of more worth then the World: thou haſt loſt Chriſt, which is richer
then this World, and ſweeter then thy life. What an infinite loſſe were
it to this World, to loſe the Sunne? 'twere at once to looſe all: 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pereunte ſolep, ereunt omnia.</hi>
               </note>
for all things ſervicea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the uſe of man, depend upon the motion and
influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of that glorious Body. What a loſſe then is it to the leſſer
World, to looſe Chriſt the Sunne of Righteouſneſſe? 'Tis to looſe
all good at once, for ſoule and body. All graces cloſe and wither when
Chriſt departs, as all fragrant flowers when the Sunne withdrawes his
influence. And when <pb n="115" facs="tcp:871:68"/>theſe flowers wither in the ſoul,
a man is a moving Dung-hill, that ſtinkes in the Noſtrils of God and man,
where ever hee comes. A man that hath loſt Chriſt, may truely ſay as
ſhee when the Arke was loſt, <hi>that his glory is departed.</hi> As the
Sunne is the glory of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter World: ſo Chriſt the Sunne of
righteouſneſſe, is the glory of the leſſer World, to wit, man.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt loſt that in the world, that is more worth then the
world, and which all the world can never helpe thee to. Thou haſt loſt that
which would have made the worſt condition in this life, a Heaven; whereas the
beſt without it, is but a hell. Thou haſt loſt that which would have
beene to thy ſoule, a continuall feaſt; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as now thy ſoul is in a
continual <pb n="116" facs="tcp:871:69"/>famine and leanneſſe. Thou haſt loſt thy
ſpirits, and thy ſoule is in a dead Palſie, ſo that thou art a living
dead man, fit for no ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſervice. Thou haſt loſt thy head, thou
haſt loſt thy eyes, thou haſt loſt thy hands, thou haſt loſt thy
feet, thou haſt loſt thy bread, thou haſt loſt thy cloathing; nay, thou
haſt loſt thy beſt father, thy beſt huſband, thy beſt friend; all
this and much more comfort is Chriſt to man. Thou haſt great reaſon then
O deſerted ſoule, to lay to heart thy loſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2.</note>Lay to heart thy loſſe, this is
comely, but do not blame Chriſt for departing from thee, this is uncomely,
and unrighteous. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comely; for it doth not ſuit with wiſdomes children, to
lay folly to their Maker. Unrighteous, for thou conſtrainſt him to depart
from thee, otherwiſe he had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <pb n="117" facs="tcp:871:69"/>left thee: thou
didſt ſin again and again of weakneſſe, and yet Chriſt as a Comforter
did not depart from thee: untill thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganſt to take <hi>pleaſure in
unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,</hi> and to make ſin a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, <hi>a right
eye,</hi> a very ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able thing unto thee, Chriſt did not leave thee.
Thou beganſt to wax wanton againſt Chriſt, and then Chriſt caſt thee
off. Thou beganſt to play the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and to backſlide in heart from
Chriſt; and then he fell off from thee, <hi>and filled thee with thine owne
wayes.</hi> Now theſe things ſeriouſly conſidered, haſt thou any
cauſe to blame Chriſt for departing from thee? It is a comely and a very
righteous thing for Wiſdomes children to juſtifie wiſdome in all his
waies, as to others, ſo to our ſelves. Wherefore thus do, O deſerted
ſoule; ſay, righteous art thou, <pb n="118" facs="tcp:871:70"/>O Chriſt in
departing from me, and righteous mayſt thou be, if thou never returne to me,
ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindly have I dealt with thee.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3.</note>Then ſet thy ſelfe ſeriouſly
to the uſe of all holy meanes, whereby thou maiſt get thy Comforter to
returne to thee. Examine thy ſoule throughly thou muſt, to finde out what
evill deprived thee of ſo great a good; and in ſerious ſoule ſearching,
God will ſpeak to thy conſcience, and conſcience will ſpeak plainly to
thee, and tell thee wherein thou didſt give diſtaſte to thy Comforter,
and what was the cauſe he forſook thy ſoule.</p>
            <p>And when thou haſt found out that evill, which conſcience tels
thee, deprived thee of ſo great a good, thou muſt fall ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry foule with it,
how ſweet ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it hath been unto thee. Thy <pb n="119" facs="tcp:871:70"/>great
worke muſt be, to bring thy heart to a holy <hi>revenge</hi> upon this ſin:
to abhorre it, and thy ſelfe becauſe of it: and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come very vile, as
<hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, and very low in thine owne eyes. Bring thy heart to
admire the infinite patience and mercy of God, that things are no worſe with
thy ſoule. That God had not cut thee off, in the acting of that ſinne for
which he deſerted thee: that he hath left any place for repentance, and given
the leaſt deſire to ſet about this work.</p>
            <p>And when thou art come thus farre, poſſibly the light of Gods
countenance may begin now and then, to glance into thy ſoul, as at ſome
little cranny: or at leaſt ſome more then ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry lightſomneſſe,
may appear in thy dark dull ſoul, as there doth in the dark morning, ſome
ſpace <pb n="120" facs="tcp:871:71"/>of time before the Sun appears, that had left this
Horizon. Now this beame of light, or this little lightſomeneſſe of
ſoule, thou muſt much admire; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge an unfathomed depth of love
in it; that God ſhould ſo much as once ſtoope, to caſt an eye after
thee more, to give thy ſoule the leaſt refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that did abuſe
flagons of love.</p>
            <p>By this glimpſe of light, or glimmering light, you are to
ſtrengthen your faith, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of this, that light will more and more
appeare, as the light of the morning unto the perfect day: and ſo
conſequently to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low God with ſo much the more fervency of prayer, for
the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne of his <hi>wonted kindneſſe. To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> you know, carried
himſelfe very roughly to his brethren which had abuſed him, for ſome 
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:871:71"/>ſpace of time; and put them in great feare of the
loſſe of their lives; told them they were Spies, and many harſh words he
gave them, and harſh looks: but at laſt, when his Brethren had brought to
him <hi>Benjamin,</hi> and diſcourſed a while, <hi>Ioſephs</hi> bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els
began to work, and he could no longer with-hold his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly love, <hi>Come
neare to me. I pray you, I am Ioſeph your brother, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.4.</note> Thus Chriſt our elder Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deales
with us, who do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindly &amp; unbrotherly uſe him: he will handle us very
roughly, and put us in fear of the loſſe of our beſt lives: he will make
our conſciences ſpeake bitter things againſt us; and let looſe the
De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill to tell us that we are <hi>Spies,</hi> hypocrites, and falſe friends
to Chriſt: in this diſtracted, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted, perplexed ſtate, hee may hold
us many dayes, many <pb n="122" facs="tcp:871:72"/>weeks, many moneths; but hee cannot
hold in his brotherly love alwayes, if wee patiently beare his frownes, and
kindly intreat him, and bring <hi>Benjamin</hi> to him, his own blood and
me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; this will make his bowels worke, and make him unmask himſelfe and
ſay, come neare to me, O mourning ſoules, toſſed and not comforted; I
am Chriſt your elder brother, whom yee unkindly uſed: in a little wrath I
hid my face from you, but now with everlaſting kindneſſe will I em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace
you.</p>
            <trailer>Trinuni Deo gloria.</trailer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:871:72"/>
            <head>CHRISTS COMMUNION with his Church Militant.</head>
            <head> 
               <q>
                  <bibl>2. Tim. 4. <hi>verſe</hi> 22.</bibl> 
                  <p>The Lord Ieſus Chriſt bee with thy ſpirit.</p>
               </q> 
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Text is <hi>Pauls</hi> ſweet affectionate farwell to
<hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy.</hi> Many grave and gracious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions <hi>Paul</hi> had
given <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy;</hi> 
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:871:73"/>but 'tis not ſo much what man
ſaith to the eare, as as what Chriſt ſaith to the heart that workes
effectually, to ſet man about his duty; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth <hi>Paul</hi> in
the concluſion of all his Chriſtian counſell to <hi>Timothy</hi>
pathetically pray, <hi>That the Lord Ieſus Chriſt would be with his
Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The beſt teaching of man, is but as water ſpilt on the ground,
unleſſe Chriſt inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teach the ſpirit. If I am taught my duty by a
<hi>Paul,</hi> one in gifts not inferiour to the chiefeſt Apoſtles, yet
unleſſe Chriſt bee with my ſpirit, to make things take roote there; all
will die and wither, like good ſeed caſt into bad ground. And therefore
<hi>Paul</hi> ſaw it but needfull, as to teach the eare, ſo to intreate the
Lord to teach and ſtrengthen the ſpirit. <hi>The <pb n="125" facs="tcp:871:73"/>Lord
Ieſus Chriſt bee with thy Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a great diſtance (you know) betweene the eare and the
heart: it is an eaſie thing for man to bring home things unto the one, but no
leſſe then the Al-mighty power of Chriſt, will bring home things unto the
other. There is an incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable hardneſſe, upon the heart of man
naturally: it is harder then an Adamant: now though a child with his little
finger, may make a dint upon dow, yet a Gyant with all his ſtrength, cannot
make dints upon an Adamant; much leſſe can all created ſtrength, make
divine impreſſions upon the ſpirit of man; and therefore it is, that
<hi>Paul</hi> doth implore an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty ſtrength to doe this, <hi>The Lord
Ieſus Chriſt bee with thy Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:871:74"/>Why doth not <hi>Paul</hi> here, wiſh
riches and honours &amp; pleaſures unto <hi>Timothy?</hi> Is the bare
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſt with a mans ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſuch a bleſſing?</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, riches and honours, &amp;c. they are
<hi>bona,</hi> but not <hi>optima:</hi> good things, but not the beſt things.
Earthly things though good in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, yet are no further forth good to
mee, then as the Lord Jeſus Chriſt is with my ſpirit, to guide it to
uſe them; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Paul</hi> as one truly wiſe, prayed for the
prime good for <hi>Timothy;</hi> for that good which makes all other things
worke together for good, to wit, <hi>That the Lord Ieſus Chriſt would bee
with his Spirit.</hi> The point I intend to ſtand on, is this, <hi>That to
have the Lord Ieſus Chriſt with our ſpirits, is a prime and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall
bleſſing. Paul</hi> here wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <pb n="127" facs="tcp:871:74"/>it to
<hi>Timothy,</hi> as a cardinall bleſſing, <hi>The Lord Ieſus Chriſt
bee with thy ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Enucleatio
propoſitionis</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>To have Chriſt with our ſpirits,
&amp;c.</hi> How can Chriſt bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with man upon Earth, who is now
aſcended, and ſitteth at the right Hand of his Father in Heaven?</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle doth hint an anſwer to this queſtion, in the
forme of his Prayer, if you obſerve it. <hi>The Lord Ieſus Chriſt ſaith
hee, be with thy ſpirit.</hi> Hee ſpeakes of ſuch a preſence, as will
fitly yeeld Communion and fellowſhip, to the ſpirit of man. There is a
double preſence of Chriſt with man, corporall and ſpirituall joyntly; or
meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirituall. With juſt men made perfect in glory, Chriſt is
corporally preſent; they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his wounded Body made a glorious Body, as a
continuall <pb n="128" facs="tcp:871:75"/>aſſurance of the Reſurrection of their
owne vile bodies, unto the ſame ſimilitude. And with them Chriſt is
preſent, ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally filling them with thoſe joyes, the taſt of which
upon Earth, is called <hi>unſpeakable and full of glory.</hi> Of this
communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſpeakes Chriſt himſelfe. <hi>I in them, and thou in mee, that
they may bee made perfect in one.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi>
17.23</note> As the ſoule is <hi>tota in toto, &amp; tota in qualibet
parte:</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the whole, in that whole which is leſſe noble
then it ſelfe: according to the whole, that is, according to that full force
and energy which the ſoule hath, it actuates and organizeth, every member of
the body, the leaſt as well as the greateſt; So Chriſt in the myſticall
body of Saints glorified, is as I may ſay, <hi>Totus in toto, &amp; totus in
qualibet parte.</hi> Whole Chriſt, <pb n="129" facs="tcp:871:75"/>doth wholy exerciſe
dominion in every glorified ſoule; hence it is, that all ſuch ſouls, are
whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly holy, and wholy happy; that is perfectly holy, and perfectly happy, for
as much as Chriſt who is the fulneſſe of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers glory, is fully
preſent with them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there is a preſence of Chriſt with man, meerly
ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall; that is, ſuch a preſence, as whereby not the perſon, but
the providence of Chriſt may bee ſeene. Such a preſence as
<hi>ſuperiora</hi> have with <hi>inferiora,</hi> not a <hi>contiguall,</hi>
but a <hi>vertuall</hi> preſence; a preſence of influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and governance,
as the Sunne hath with us, by his rayes and beames. And this preſence is
either <hi>commune</hi> or <hi>ſpeciall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Commune preſence of Chriſt with man, is that wherby 
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:871:76"/>man is upheld and guided, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the being of a
ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall creature. Of this preſence of Chriſt with man, ſpeakes the
Apoſtle, <hi>that they ſhould ſeeke the Lord, if happily they might feele
after him and ſinde him, though hee bee not farre from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of us, for
in him we live, move, and have our being.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts
17.27.28.</note> Chriſt as an upholder of each creature, is not far from
every one of us; that is, hee is ſtill preſent with us thus, and <hi>with
all Nations of men, which hee hath made of one bloud, to dwell upon the face of
the Earth.</hi> This preſence of Chriſt with man therefore, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
properly bee called a <hi>prime</hi> and <hi>principall bleſſing,</hi> a
choiſe and ſpeciall favour, becauſe it is Commune to man-kinde in
generall; yea Commune to all Creatures below man; for God is with all the
workes of his <pb n="131" facs="tcp:871:76"/>Handes, to uphold every Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture according
to its proper ſpecies.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there is a ſpeciall preſence of Chriſt with man
which is that efficacious work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, of the Spirit of Chriſt in the ſpirit
of man, whereby it is made one ſpirit, with the Spirit of Chriſt, in
willing and nilling, according to that of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>Hee that is
joyned to the Lord, is one ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a ſpeciall preſence of Chriſt, with the bodies of
men, for the good of them; which the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> intimates where hee
ſaith, <hi>that hee knowes our frame, and remembers that wee are but duſt:
and that the Angells of the Lord pitch their Tents about the righteous.</hi>
And <hi>Iacob</hi> found the truth of this by experience, when hee fled before
<hi>Eſan,</hi> and ſlept ſo ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <pb n="132" facs="tcp:871:77"/>upon a
ſtone. But this ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and ſpeciall preſence and providence of Chriſt,
reſpecting the outward man, is compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended under the other, which
reſpects the inward man, as <hi>quid minus ſub majori,</hi> a leſſe
bleſſing under a greater. For if God bee in a ſpeciall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner preſent
with my ſpirit, to guide and order that unto all Holy wayes, my ſpirit will
command my body to walke in them too; and ſo conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Chriſt cannot
chuſe, but be tenderly preſent with my body alſo, for the good of that,
whilſt every member thereof, is actuated by a ſpirit of his owne ordering,
to his owne honour, <hi>as weapons of Righteouſneſſe.</hi> And therefore
doth <hi>Paul</hi> (pithily to ſpeake much in few) ſilent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſſe over
that, which is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily preſuppoſed, praying <pb n="133" facs="tcp:871:77"/>that Chriſt would bee with <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothies</hi> ſpirit, and then he
was ſure, Chriſt would bee after a ſpeciall manner preſent, with his
body too, for the good of that. <hi>The Lord Ieſus Chriſt bee with thy
ſpirit.</hi> That is, <hi>the Lord Ieſus Chriſt exerciſe a ſpeciall
do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion in thy ſpirit, for the guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ordering of it, unto the
avoyding of all evill, and to the performing of all good, whereby Chriſt may
have all the glory, due to his Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that thus to have Chriſt preſent with a mans ſpirit, is
a prime and principall bleſſing, I will plainely demonſtrate to you, by a
triple argument ab effectu.</p>
            <p>Thus to have Chriſt preſent with our ſpirits, is the ready
way to all temporall, ſpirituall, and eternall good: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt
needes bee a prime <pb n="134" facs="tcp:871:78"/>and principall bleſſing. Thus to
have Chriſt preſent with a mans ſpirit, is the ready way un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all
temporall good. Men whoſe ſpirits, Chriſt doth after a ſpeciall manner
order, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void ſinne, and to <hi>keepe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves pure,</hi> as
<hi>Paul</hi> here uſeth the expreſſion to <hi>Timothy,</hi> all
temporall good things, ſo farre forth as may be good for them, belong unto
them by promiſe; <hi>For godlineſſe hath the promiſe of this life. It
ſhall come to paſſe</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>if you walke in my wayes,
that I will bleſſe you in the fruite of the Wombe, in the fruit of the
Field, in the basket and ſtore, &amp;c. If you walke in my wayes I will doe
this, &amp;c.</hi> Why, they with whoſe ſpirits Chriſt is after a
ſpeciall manner preſent, this is their <hi>high way</hi> (as
<hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith) <hi>to depart from evill:</hi> that is, this is their
daily endevour, to <pb n="135" facs="tcp:871:78"/>walke in all the wayes of the Lord; and
ſo conſequently, all temporall good of right be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs unto them.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, how is it then, that thoſe with whoſe
ſpirits Chriſt is moſt preſent, to make moſt tender for his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,
have uſually leaſt of all temporall good things?</p>
            <p>To this the anſwer is eaſie and manifold. Men with whoſe
ſpirits Chriſt is moſt preſent, to make them moſt tender to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voide
ſinne, and to keepe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves pure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, theſe the Divell doth moſt of all maligne, and ſets his
limmes to <hi>ſpoile them of their goods,</hi> as the Author to the
<hi>Hebrewes</hi> ſaith, to keepe them from that, which Chriſt would have
them advanced to, or elſe to ſtrip them of that, which Chriſt hath
conferred on them, by impriſonment, baniſhment <pb n="136" facs="tcp:871:79"/>and the
like; and ſo make ſuch live in Dens, and Holes, and Caves of the Earth; to
wander in Deſerts and Wilderneſſes, wearing Sheeps-skins, and
Goateſ-skins, of whom the World is not worthy. Where a ſpirit of malice and
confuſion rules, tis no marvell to ſee ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants ſet on horſe-back,
and Princes goe on foote.</p>
            <p>Secondly, men with whoſe ſpirit Chriſt is after a ſpeciall
manner preſent, he takes ſpecial notice to what evill the ſpirit is
moſt enclined, &amp; ſo anſwerably gives of theſe outward things unto
them. A wiſe Father hath his eye upon the diſpoſition of his child, and
to what exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancy he finds him enclined, he labours to prevent all
occaſions to it, and ſo keeps his child ſhort of what hee could
otherwiſe liberally allow him. And thus <pb n="137" facs="tcp:871:79"/>'tis with our
heavenly Father, reſpecting his children: he eyes ſtrictly their ſpirits,
and if he ſee them inclined to pride, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, or any other
ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous vice, hee ſhortens them in that, which may foment theſe. At
this (I thinke) <hi>Iames</hi> may point, where he ſaith, <hi>Let the rich
rejoyce in that he is made low.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames</hi>
1.10</note> God out of tender love to his children, oft times makes them poore
in purſe, that they may become poore in ſpirit, and ſo capable of the
Kingdome of Heaven. Which rightly weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is not matter of ſorrow, but
matter of joy, as <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, thoſe with whoſe ſpirits Chriſt is after a
ſpeciall manner preſent, to guide them to walke in his wayes, and to keepe
themſelves pure, Chriſt doth prove them by poverty, as by other things; and
hence it <pb n="138" facs="tcp:871:80"/>may come to paſſe, that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans very
holy, may yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding be very deſtitute of the things of this
life. Thus you know the Lord dealt with <hi>Iob.</hi> Chriſt was after a
ſpeciall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner preſent with his Spirit, to guide him to walke uprightly
above many in his time; now to make knowne this to the world, to his own glory,
and <hi>Iobs</hi> eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall honour, he ſtript <hi>Iob</hi> of all, and ſet
him upon a dunghill, who before ſat with the chiefeſt in ſeats of honour.
God will have the world know, that thoſe with whoſe ſpirits hee is after
a ſpecial manner preſent, to guide and order them, are not as thoſe with
whoſe ſpirits the devill is in a ſpeciall manner preſent, to guide and
order; to wit, ſuch as will winde and turne every way when put to it.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, thoſe with whoſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits <pb n="139" facs="tcp:871:80"/>Chriſt is after a ſpeciall manner preſent, they deſire but
little of the things of this life; and therefore 'tis no marvell, to ſee
Chriſtians very holy, yet not very wealthy. Chriſtians with whoſe
ſpirit Chriſt is after a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall manner preſent, they only deſire
daily bread; <hi>Agurs</hi> porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, food convenient; and this the Lord gives
them, and with this they are contented, which is the only wealthy eſtate.
Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, with whoſe ſpirit Chriſt is after a ſpeciall manner
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, <hi>they hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſſe,</hi> not
after riches in the world: they <hi>covet the beſt gifts,</hi> the
unſearchable riches of Chriſt, and not the fading riches of this life. Now
Chriſt applyes himſelfe, to be moſt liberall in the diſtribution of
that, which the ſpirits of men moſt bend af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; in mercy, or in juſtice.
Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians <pb n="140" facs="tcp:871:81"/>whoſe ſpirits moſt ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bend
after grace, to theſe Chriſt in mercy doth moſt bountifully apply
himſelfe, to give grace; according to that of Chriſt, <hi>Bleſſed are
they that hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſſe, for they ſhall bee
filled.</hi> Chriſtians whoſe ſpirits moſt ſtrongly bend after
worldly riches, to theſe oft times Chriſt in juſtice moſt liberally
applies himſelfe to give thoſe, according to that of the Pſalmiſt,
<hi>Whoſe belly thou filleſt with thy hid treaſure.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.14</note> Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding likewiſe to that of
<hi>Solomon, There is a ſore evill which I have ſeene under the Sun,
namely, riches kept for the owners thereof to their hurt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.13.</note> The objection being thus anſwered,
the argument is ſtill of force. That to have Chriſt with our ſpirits, is
the way to all temporall good, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, <hi>a prime and
principall bleſſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:871:81"/>But that I may yet more fully ſpeak in this
argument, note that temporall good, is either poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, or privative; (if I
may for illuſtrations ſake ſo diſtinguiſh.) Temporall good in a
poſitive ſenſe, is that ſecular thing, which is in it ſelfe good; as
bread and cloathing, and the like, of which we have already ſpoken.</p>
            <p>Temporall good privatively ſo called, is affliction ordered to a
mans good, which in it ſelfe is not ſo. Now all thoſe with whoſe
ſpirits Chriſt is preſent, are partakers of this temporall good. All
outward loſſes and croſſes, tend to their inward gaine, becauſe
Chriſt is with their ſpirits. For all outward troubles, are heavier or
lighter, more hurtfull or more profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſtill to a man, as Chriſt is
pleaſed to order his Spirit under them. A little outward trouble, 
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:871:82"/>if Chriſt let it ſeize upon a mans ſpirit, he
quickly ſinks and dyes under his burthen, according to that of the Apoſtle,
<hi>worldly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row cauſeth death.</hi> The loſſe of a wife or husband;
nay the loſſe of a child or friend; nay the loſſe of the leaſt
outward content, if Chriſt ſtand aloofe from a mans ſpirit, and let it
faſten upon him, hee will ſoone languiſh, and bleed inwardly to death;
where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as all outward afflictions, meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together upon the outward man, if
Chriſt be with the ſpirit, to ſupport and beare up that, a Chriſtian
ſweetly ſubmits, and keeps on his way, according to that of the Apoſtle,
<hi>Rejoycing in hope, patient in tribulation, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing inſtant in
prayer.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.12</note> Now Chriſt tenderly
watches, when outward troubles begin to take hold of that Spirit, with whom he
is ſpecially preſent, and then <pb n="143" facs="tcp:871:82"/>he quickly releeves and
eaſes it; and not only ſo, but ſanctifies it, to the drawing of ſuch a
ſpirit nearer to God in love; accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that of <hi>David, I love the
Lord, becauſe hee hath heard my voice, and my ſupplications, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he
hath inclined his eare unto me, therefore will I call upon him as long as I
live.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.1,2.</note> Adde this to the
former, that to have Chriſt with our ſpirits, is the ready way to all
temporall good, whether <hi>poſitive,</hi> or <hi>privative;</hi> and you
muſt needs grant it to be a prime and principall bleſſing.</p>
            <p>Secondly, thoſe with whoſe ſpirits Chriſt is ſpecially
preſent, are in the ready way to all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall good; and therefore thus
to have Chriſt preſent with our ſpirits, muſt needs be counted a prime
and principall bleſſing. Chriſt is the Author and worker of all grace;
and therefore ſuch <pb n="144" facs="tcp:871:83"/>ſpirits muſt needs be very
graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous with whom Chriſt is. <hi>The places are holy whereunto the Ark of
the Lord hath come,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2
<hi>Chron.</hi> 8.11.</note> I may truly ſay it of Chriſt, which the Ark
typified. The Spirits are holy with whom Chriſt is, and where holy Chriſt
comes. They are at the Well-head for holineſſe, which have holy Chriſt
with their ſpirits.</p>
            <p>They that have Chriſt with their ſpirits, are in the ready way
to the very heigth of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly wiſdome; for there is no ſuch teacher of
wiſdome as Chriſt is. With him are all the treaſures of wiſdome. He
that lyes in thy boſome, teaching thee wiſdome ſecretly, came out of the
very boſome of the Almighty, &amp; knowes all things; and he gives ſuch an
unction to that Spirit w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> he teaches, that he makes it know and diſcerne
all things too.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:871:83"/>They that have Chriſt with their ſpirits,
are in the ready way to the very height of love, which is the glory of all
graces, in the ſight of God and man; for there is no ſuch worker and winner
of love, as Chriſt is. If he doe but <hi>put in his finger by the hole of the
dore,</hi> hee will make a mans bowels melt after him. If hee doe but reveale
his love to our ſpirits a little, our ſpirits grow ſick of love unto him.
He will wound us with one of his eyes; ſo full of beauty is he. Let a mans
ſpirit bee never ſo cold, yet if Chriſt be with it, hee is in the ready
way to burne with love to Chriſt, as ſtrong as death, which many waters
cannot quench.</p>
            <p>They that have Chriſt with their ſpirits, are in the ready way
to the very heigth of joy &amp; conſolation: they are in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy 
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:871:84"/>way to joy <hi>unſpeakable and full of glory. Theſe
things have I ſpoken unto you, that your joy may be full,</hi> ſaid
Chriſt to his Diſciples. Chriſt ſpeaks ſuch things to the ſpirits
of thoſe with whom hee is preſent, as fils their ſpirits with joy, to the
very brim; and this oft times in the very depth of all outward extremity. The
Church doth darkly hint this. <hi>The Comforter which ſhould relieve my
ſoule is far from me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.16.</note> As if
the Church had ſaid, though my outward miſery bee exceeding great, yet if
the Comforter did but keepe cloſe to my ſpirit, I ſhould have as much
conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as my heart could hold, in the midſt of all my miſery; but
this is my miſery of miſeries, that the Comforter w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſhould relieve my
ſoule is far from me: out of the hearing of ſighes and groanes: nay out of
the hearing <pb n="147" facs="tcp:871:84"/>of ſtrong cryes; <hi>he is angry againſt
my prayers.</hi> In a word a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an which hath Chriſt with his
ſpirit, is in the ready way to <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell in vertue,</hi> as <hi>David</hi>
ſayes: to excell in all vertue; to be wiſer then his teachers; more
excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in all grace, then his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. And therefore, to have Chriſt
preſent with our ſpirits, muſt needs be counted and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>A prime
and principall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, to have Chriſt with our ſpirits, is the ready way
unto eternall good; and therefore a prime and principall bleſſing. As a
ſtone carries with it, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever light thing be faſtned to it, unto its
own center; ſo Chriſt whoſe proper place of reſidence is Heaven,
carries with him thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, all ſuch ſpirits as to whom he is united on
earth. If we have a ſpeciall friend at Court, wee <pb n="148" facs="tcp:871:85"/>count
that wee are in a ready way to ſee all the pompe of the Prince. Chriſt hath
the Keyes of Heaven and Hell; hee opens and no man ſhuts; ſhuts, and no man
can open: all with whoſe ſpirits he hath dwelt, and beene kindly uſed
upon earth, hee knowes; and when they ſhall knock at thoſe everlaſting
gates, hee will open and let them in to every roome in his royall dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
and ſhew them all the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry which he had with his Father before the world
was. 'Tis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Chriſt and that ſpirit with whom he lives, as between
<hi>Naomi</hi> and <hi>Ruth:</hi> where the one lives the other will. Whileſt
ſuch ſpirits live in the body, Chriſt will live with them there; when
they remove out of the body, Chriſt will not leave them <hi>(death cannot
ſeparate)</hi> but commands his Angels, to bring them to <pb n="149" facs="tcp:871:85"/>eternall manſions, with himſelf. Chriſt which is lifted up to
glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry himſelfe, will draw all ſuch unto him, as in whoſe ſpirits he
dwels, and no ſtrength ſhall bee able to withſtand him; none ſhall
pluck ſuch out of his hand. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nio cum Chriſto, eſt unio
inuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If to have Chriſt with our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits bee a grand favour, not to
have him with our ſpirits, muſt needs be a grand evill. A ſpirit without
Chriſt is naked, as a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy without cloathes. Many things may make cloathing
and defence for the body, but only Chriſt that <hi>beſt garment,</hi> as
the Father of the Prodigall cals him, can make cloathing and munition for the
ſoule. A mans ſpirit without Chriſt is as a naked body amongſt thorns,
every thorne pierceth, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bryer ſcratcheth, and fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth 
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:871:86"/>blood from ſuch a body; ſo worldly cares and worldly
fears, when ſtrong, will pierce ſuch a naked ſpirit thorow and tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,
and make him runne mad, if God (unſought) do not ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably ſtep in
and bridle the Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam. A mans ſpirit without Chriſt, is as a naked body
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Serpents; every Serpent ſtings and venomes ſuch a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked body to
death; ſo every ſeed of the Serpent ſtings and poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to death,
ſuch naked ſoules, by their threatnings, flatteries, examples, and the
like. A mans ſpirit without Chriſt, is as a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked body in great blaſts
of light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; ſuch bodies are ſuddenly ſcorcht and conſumed; ſo
ſuch naked ſoules are ſuddenly blaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by the fiery darts of the
De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, and ſo ſuddenly oft times goe from burning to burning; from
burning in ſin, to burning in hell.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:871:86"/>A mans ſpirit without Chriſt is not only
naked, but blind too. A naked man having his ſight, may make ſome ſhift,
but a man naked and blind too, is in a miſerable helpeleſſe ſtate
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: and juſt ſuch is the ſtate and condition of every mans ſpirit,
that hath not Chriſt with it: for as the Sunne in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, is the eye
and light of the greater World; ſo the Sunne of righteouſneſſe
Chriſt, is the eye &amp; light of the leſſer world, man. Now doe but
imagine what a darke dolorous condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wee ſhould all bee in, if the Sunne
were darkned, or had utterly forſaken our Horizon; or doe but thinke of that
dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which was upon the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> for a little time, when
no man could ſtirre out of his place; and ſuch and much worſe is the
darke dolorous conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <pb n="352" facs="tcp:871:87"/>of a ſpirit without Chriſt;
not able to ſee the leaſt beame of ſaving light; not able to ſtir a
ſteppe out of his place, in the way that leads to life.</p>
            <p>A mans ſpirit without Chriſt is not onely blind, but dumme
too. A man that is blind, yet if he can ſpeake, can begge for that which hee
cannot ſee to worke. But when a man is blind, and dumme too; that hee can
neither helpe himſelfe, nor beg others, hee is in a dolefull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
indeed; and juſt ſuch is the condition of every mans ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that hath
not Chriſt with it. For as Chriſt is Eyes to the ſoule, ſo hee is a
Mouth and Tongue, enabling it to cry <hi>Abba Father.</hi> Unleſſe the
ſpirit of Chriſt be with our ſpirits, help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our infirmities, who are
god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; we are dumme, and not able to ſpeake to our owne Father, 
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:871:87"/>as adopted children, for daily Bread; much more unable to
begge for life, to the dreadfull Judge of all the World, muſt all ungodly
perſons needes bee, whoſe ſpirits are altogether without Chriſt, as an
helper. I would have all men that live in their ſinnes, thinke ſeriouſly
of this; when Chriſt as the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Judge of all the World, at the great
day ſhall aske you, what you have to ſay for your ſelves, that you
ſhould not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally die for your ſinnes, in which you have lived, you
will bee like that man which was without his wedding garment, dumme and not
able to ſay a word for your ſelves, becauſe Chriſt is not with your
ſpirits. 'Tis impoſſible that a mans own guilty ſpirit, ſhould bee
able to looke the terrible judge of men and divells in the face, much 
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:871:88"/>leſſe ſpeake a word for mercy, unleſſe the
Al-mighty ſpirit of Chriſt be with it, to aid it. Many ignorant wretches,
ſooth them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with this, that they will at laſt cry, Lord Lord, and
ſo prevaile quickly for pardon, with him who is infinite in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. Why, but
thinke on this O ignorant ſoule! <hi>No man can call Ieſus Lord but by the
Holy-Ghoſt.</hi> Thou wilt not in thy greateſt need, bee able to cry Lord
Lord, unleſſe the Lord bee with thy ſpirit. Death will ſting thee,
conſcience will gnaw thee, Chriſt will condemne thee, Divels will teare
thee; and yet wilt not thou bee able to cry, Lord, Lord, have mercy on me,
unleſſe the Lord bee with thy ſpirit: but inſtead of crying Lord, Lord,
for mercy, thou wilt burne in malice againſt the Lord, and curſe and
blaſpheme <pb n="155" facs="tcp:871:88"/>as Divels and damned wretches doe. Haſt thou
never ſeene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned wretches, not onely dumme, but withall deſperate
too, and leape off the ladder themſelves, without either ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God or man
forgiveneſſe? thus in a ſpirituall ſenſe, and much worſe, wilt thou
doe in the great day of judgement, for as much as Chriſt is not with thy
ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, a mans ſpirit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſt, is not onely blind
and dumme, but deafe too. And if a man bee blind and dumme, yet if hee can
heare, hee may make ſome ſhift to help him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: wee follow a thing (you
know) ſometimes by the ſound, when wee cannot ſee it, nor ſpeake what
it is: but when a man is naked, blind, dumme, and deafe too, hee is in a
help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe condition indeed; and juſt <pb n="156" facs="tcp:871:89"/>ſuch is the
ſtate of a mans ſpirit without Chriſt. For Chriſt as hee is Eyes and
Tongue, ſo hee is eares alſo to the ſoule of man. Hence it is that
<hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeakes ſo frequently of ſpirituall hearing, after a
<hi>Hypotheticall</hi> manner: <hi>Hee that hath an eare, &amp;c.</hi> That is,
if any man have ſpirituall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning, <hi>let him heare what the ſpirit
ſaith to the Churches.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating that a ſpirituall eare, is a very
rare thing to bee found; that which no man hath, but hee which hath Chriſt
with his Spirit; that hath had his eares <hi>boared</hi> by the Spirit of
Chriſt, as the Scripture ſpeakes; all others are as deafe as Adders, and
can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not heare the voyce of the charmer, charme hee never ſo wiſely. I would
have all that live in their ſinnes, ſeriouſly conſider this too, as a
further degree of unhappineſſe. You <pb n="157" facs="tcp:871:89"/>tell us that you
will turne from your ſinnes hereafter, and obey the call of God in the
Miniſtry of his Word: but let mee aske you this; have you not hither unto
turned the deafe eare upon God? yes: I and ſo you will doe for the time to
come; and the reaſon of both, the ſame; becauſe Chriſt is not with your
ſpirits. Let mercies call, corrections call; let friends call, father call,
mother call; husband call, wife call; let Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters call, conſcience call;
nay let Chriſt himſelfe call, in what voyce hee will, ſtill voyce, or
lowd voyce, in words never ſo pleaſing, or never ſo piercing, yet wilt
not thou heare; becauſe Chriſt is not with thy ſpirit; but with
<hi>Salomons</hi> foole, wilt on in thy ſins, and bee eternally
pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, a mans ſpirit without <pb n="158" facs="tcp:871:90"/>Chriſt, is
without <hi>feeling;</hi> in a dead Palſie all over, which how dolorous
ſuch a ſtate is, in a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall ſenſe, you know; much more dolorous in
a ſpirituall ſenſe, I am ſure. As the ſpirit of man can neither
ſee, ſpeake nor heare, ſo neither can it feele, without the ſpirit of
Chriſt. The ſpirit of man without the ſpirit of God, is dead. Chriſt is
to our ſpirits, as our ſpirits are unto our bodies, their life; and life is
the principle of feeling: for the dead feele nothing. <hi>When Chriſt which
is our [life] ſhall appeare,</hi> &amp;c. Where there is no Chriſt, there
is no life; and where there is no life, there is no feeling. You know the
Apoſtle ſpeakes of ſome that were <hi>paſt feeling,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<hi>given themſelves over to laſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civiouſneſſe, to worke all
unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with greedineſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.9.</note> There the Apoſtle ſpeakes of
ſuch a ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſeneſſe, <pb n="159" facs="tcp:871:90"/>as lyes upon the
ſoule by a ſecond act of divine juſtice. All humane ſpirits by the
firſt act of divine juſtice upon <hi>Adam,</hi> are naturally paſt
feeling, and would give up themſelves unto all wickedneſſe with
greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, did not God reſtraine. To bee paſt feeling in this latter
ſenſe, notes principally a want of divine affection; when ſinne doth not
kindly affect the ſoule with ſorrow; as in the former ſenſe, when
ſinne doth not at all affect the ſoule with ſorrow: when holy wayes and
works do not kindly affect the ſoule with joy; as in the other ſenſe,
when they do not affect the ſoul with joy at all; but rather diſturbe and
provoke to paſſion and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice.</p>
            <p>I would have all that live in their ſins, ſeriouſly think on
this alſo, as a further degree of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happineſſe. <pb n="160" facs="tcp:871:91"/>You
have heard ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny powerfull Sermons, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> you have ſeene work admirably up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
others, &amp; yet they have made no impreſſions upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your ſpirits; &amp;
many hundred more may you heare, and no divine impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at laſt be
made; and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of both, one and the ſame; becauſe Chriſt is not
with your ſpirits; and by reaſon of this, your hearts are as Adamants,
which every ſtroke hardens, but not breaks it. Let the maſter ſmite and
the man ſmite; let God ſmite, and his Miniſters ſmite, and conſcience
ſmite; nay, let every member of the body bee ſmitten with puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to
affect the ſoule with ſin, yet will it not ſtir and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine,
unleſſe Chriſt be with it.</p>
            <p>Finally a mans ſpirit without Chriſt, is without taſting or
ſmelling: to theſe ſenſes alſo <pb n="161" facs="tcp:871:91"/>(you know) the
Scripture doth allude, and therefore fitly here may, I to ſet forth fully,
the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy condition of every ſpirit without Chriſt. You know the
Apoſtle ſpeaks of ſome, <hi>that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured not the things of God;</hi>
which is a terme applyed in Scripture, to the ſenſe of ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling as well
as to the ſenſe of taſting, and therefore for brevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſake do I here
joyne both ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes together, in a ſpiritull way of alluſion. Why all
that have not Chriſt with their ſpirits, are ſuch as cannot rightly
<hi>ſavour ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall things;</hi> ſuch <hi>put bitter for ſweet, and
ſweet for bitter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I would have all you that live in your ſins, ſeriouſly
thinke on this too, as a further degree of unhappineſſe. You come oft times
to Wiſdomes houſe, and though ſhee prepare you all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall
dainties, yet you can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh <pb n="162" facs="tcp:871:92"/>nothing, but ſome by
things, that lye about the diſh, rather for ornament, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for food. And
would you know the reaſon of this? 'tis becauſe Chriſt is not with your
ſpirits. If Chriſt were with you, you wold feed on eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſh at
wiſdomes table, on promiſes, yea &amp; on threatnings too: <hi>To the
hungry ſoule, every bitter thing is ſweet,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</hi>
All that is good and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome goes downe well, where Chriſt is with the
Spirit. You come frequently to Wiſdomes houſe, who keeps a Table here and
'twere for a King, and yet you have leane ſhrivel'd ſoules, like men in a
Conſumption: eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one tels you, that you look as if you were ſtarved,
ſpeak and live, as if you never heard a good Sermon from yeares end, to
yeares end: they tell you that you are ſo leane and feeble, that 
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:871:92"/>you need the benefit of all the ſpirits, that every
diſh at wiſdoms table can yeeld, to ſtrengthen you, and recover you, and
yet every diſh almoſt goes againſt your ſtomacks; and that you doe eat,
is without ſavour or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vertue, and ſo you languiſh with al
dainties before you; and thus you will goe on languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, untill you quite
conſume &amp; periſh eternally, unleſſe Chriſt be with your
ſpirits.</p>
            <p>You ſee (I ſuppoſe) plainly by this time, that as it is a
prime and principall happineſſe to have Chriſt with our ſpirits, ſo
it is a prime and principall evill and unhappines, not to have Chriſt with
our ſpirits. Wherefore ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving laid open both before you, let mee entreat you
all to looke in upon your ſpirits, and ſee who keeps company with them,
Chriſt or the divell; one of theſe <pb n="164" facs="tcp:871:93"/>two is with all our
ſpirits. If Chriſt bee not with our ſpirits, the divellis and wil be. If
Chriſt be with your ſpirits, according to the ſenſe and meaning of the
Apoſtle in my text, you ſhall find it by theſe two things, <hi>the body
is dead becauſe of ſin; and the ſpirit is life becauſe of
righteouſnes.</hi> 'Tis <hi>Pauls</hi> Character of Chriſts ſpeciall
preſence in the ſoule of man upon earth, and therefore of ſtrong
authority. <hi>And if Chriſt be in you, the body is dead becauſe of
ſinne, but the ſpirit is life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of Righteouſneſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.10</note> The body is dead becauſe of ſinne:
that is, the body of corruption is deſtroyed, as in reſpect of the guilt of
it, ſo in reſpect of the dominion of it. And <hi>the ſpirit is life
becauſe of righteouſneſſe:</hi> that is, the regenerate part is
<hi>vige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous,</hi> in reference to all righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wayes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:871:93"/>And if therefore you would know whether
Chriſt bee with your ſpirits, ſee whether your bodies bee dead becauſe
of ſin: whether you labour to bring <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thought into ſubjection to
Chriſt;</hi> or whether you doe not <hi>allow</hi> your ſelves liberty to
ſome evill, out of love to ſome plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or profit; which is that
prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally, wherein the dominion of ſinne conſiſteth; as <hi>Paul</hi>
hints unto us, where he ſaith, <hi>the evill which I doe, I allow not.</hi>
That is, I doe not approve of it in my heart, nor plead for it with my tongue;
but ſtrive againſt it with all my ſtrength; and it would be more joy to
me, to be rid of it, then if I had a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome conferred on me. This is the
language right, of one that hath Chriſt with his ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſee whether your <hi>ſpirits be alive becauſe of
righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> 
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:871:94"/>if you would know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Chriſt be with your ſpirits, or not. See whether holy wayes doe heartily
affect you. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced when they ſaid, come let us goe to the houſe of the
Lord, ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt.</hi> He ſpake like a man, having Chriſt
indeed with his ſpirit: his ſpirit leapt within him, like the Babe in
<hi>Elizabeths</hi> Wombe, when they ſpake of drawing neere to God, in the
duties of his worſhip. A Chriſtian that hath Chriſt with his ſpirit,
ſees a taking tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant beauty in all wiſedomes wayes; <hi>they are
all wayes of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and pathes of peace;</hi> which is ſpoken in
reference to ſuch as have Chriſt with their ſpirits: for others finde no
ſuch thing in them. And his ſpirit opens in them like flowers in the Sunne,
and ſmelles fragrantly: he bends and cleaves to them, in love to 
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:871:94"/>that ſoule ſweetneſſe, which he findes in them.
And if you finde theſe things in you, I thinke I may ſafely tell you to
your comfort, that Chriſt is with your ſpirits.</p>
            <p>I may turne this Character into another forme, as <hi>Paul</hi>
doth, and tell you in his words, that <hi>hee which is joyned to the Lord is
one ſpirit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17.</note> They that
have Chriſt with their ſpirits, are one ſpirit with Chriſt. This
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion (I conceive) is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing explained by theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
words; <hi>And the multitude of them that believed, were of one heart and one
ſoule:</hi>
               <note place="margin">4 <hi>Acts v.</hi> 32.</note> or as the
ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall hath it <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>heart and
ſoule one.</hi> They that have Chriſt with their ſpirits, are heart and
ſoule one with Chriſt. They doe <hi>idem velle &amp; idem nolle.</hi> What
Chriſt loves, they love; and what Chriſt hates <pb n="168" facs="tcp:871:95"/>they
hate. Chriſt loves righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and hates iniquity: <hi>Thou haſt
loved righteouſneſſe and hated iniquity, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.7.</note> They that have Chriſt with their
ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, are heart and ſoule one with Chriſt in this. They love
righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, that is, all righteous wayes: and hate iniquity; that is
all that Gods Word con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes. 'Twas Chriſts meate and drinke, to doe his
Fathers Will; they that have Chriſt with their ſpirits, are one ſpirit
with Chriſt in this: <hi>'Tis joy to the juſt to doe judgement,</hi>
ſaith <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon.</hi> Chriſt was tender about keeping the leaſt
Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,, as well as about keeping the greateſt. <hi>Whoſoever
ſhall break one of theſe leaſt Commandements, and teach men ſo, he
ſhall be called the leaſt in the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.19</note> They that have Chriſt with their
ſpirits, are heart and ſoule <pb n="169" facs="tcp:871:95"/>one with Chriſt in
this; they are tender to keepe all Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, leaſt, as well as
greateſt. <hi>So ſhall I not be confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, whil'ſt I have refpect unto
all thy Commandements,</hi> ſaith <hi>David.</hi> I doe conceive the place
fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited ſo, as if Chriſt did account of one part of his Fathers wil
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove another: I rather thinke that hee there ſpeakes <hi>Phariſaeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
more,</hi> in the Phariſes dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, who would make the world believe, that
they mightily la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to keepe ſome precepts, but others they thought, as
many of us now doe, that they need not to bee ſo ſtrict about. Now
Chriſts tender Spirit for his Fathers honour, could not brooke this halting
in religion; and they that have Chriſt with their ſpirits, are heart and
ſoule one with Chriſt in this. That Commandement which the 
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:871:96"/>moſt ſay is one of the <hi>leaſt,</hi> and may be
diſpenſed with all; or at leaſt need not bee ſo ſtrictly look't unto;
that, as well as any other, whil'ſt a precious part of Chriſts will, a man
that hath Chriſt with his ſpirit, will bee tender to obſerve.
<hi>Davids</hi> ſpirit ſmote him, for cutting off the lap of <hi>Sauls</hi>
garment, as wel as for cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off the life of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rijah:</hi> which
plainly ſhewes, that men which have Chriſt with their ſpirits, are tender
about the avoiding of ſmall ſins, as well as great.</p>
            <p>Now poſſibly ſome of you by what hath beene ſaid, may
ſee, that as yet you have not Chriſt with your ſpirits; I ſhall
addreſſe my ſelfe in the firſt place, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to ſpeake to you;
and then in the ſecond place, I ſhall addreſſe my ſelfe, particularly
to ſpeake to ſuch of you, as have by what hath beene ſaid diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, 
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:871:96"/>that Chriſt is indeed with your ſpirits. To you which
by what hath been ſaid, ſee, that as yet Chriſt is not with your
ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, I have only theſe two things to ſay, labour to bewaile your
great want, as perſons deeply ſenſible of it; and then labour to get this
grant ſpeedily ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed.</p>
            <p>Firſt, labour to bewaile your great want, as perſons deeply
affected with it. 'Tis the greateſt want in the World, to want Chriſt to
bee with a mans ſpirit. Other wants may bee afflicting wants, but this is a
damning want. Other wants may make thee deſpiſed of men, but this want will
make thee for ever to be abhorr'd of God. Thou were better want riches, thou
were better want honours; nay, thou were better want bread to put in thy head,
then want Chriſt to <pb n="172" facs="tcp:871:97"/>bee in thy heart. Thou were better
want thy deere Husband, thy ſweete Wife, to lye in thy beſome, then want
Chriſt to lye there. Nay, thy ſoule were better to bee without thy body,
them without Chriſt. If there bee any want under Heaven, that makes a hell to
a man, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth, it is this, to want Chriſt to bee with his ſpirit. For
what is it that makes hell, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
place full of ſin, and full of miſery but this, that Chriſt is not with
thoſe ſpirits: they are ſpirits everlaſtingly excluded, from all
communion with Chriſt. Now whereas great wanes, make you complaine heavily,
and mourne bitterly, begge the Lord to make theſe things ſinke into your
ſpirits, that you may bee ſenſible of this great want of wants, that your
ſpirits are without Chriſt, <pb n="173" facs="tcp:871:97"/>and ſo without God in
this world; that ſo all ſorrow for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wants, may meete and run in one
channell, to bewa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e this great
want. <hi>Sauls</hi> ſpeech to his ſervant, I may here
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ly allude to, <hi>Come let us
returne</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>leaſt my Father lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> caring for the Aſſes, and take thought for
us.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1 5</note> If you that mourne for
this want, and that want, did but feele the want of Chriſt with your
ſpirits, you would with <hi>Kiſh</hi> quickely leave mourning for trifles
and begin to mourne for things of waight. Come, O my ſoule! ceaſe mourning
for Father, and Mother; ceaſe mourning for Husband and Wife, for Children and
ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; and begin to mourne for this, that thou yet liveſt
Chriſtleſſe, and art in the ready way to die and periſh
remedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:871:98"/>When you have got your hearts to bleed
inwardly, under your great want; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cry mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Lord, to ſupply
it. And to make your prayers prevalent, urge the promiſe of God, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hee
hath engaged himſelfe to do good in Chriſt, to them that are <hi>afar
off.</hi> Thy ſoule thou fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt far off from Chriſt: why, the promiſe
(ſaith the Apoſtle) of Chriſt, and ſalvation by him, is to ſuch.
<hi>For the promiſe is to you and to your children, and to all that are [afar
off.]</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39.</note> This <hi>Peter</hi>
ſpake by way of comfort, as now I do, to ſuch as felt their ſpirits
with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſt; without grace and hope of glory. Chriſt you ſee is under
promiſe, under a generall promiſe, and therefore no ſoule ſhould
deſpaire of obtaining him. Hee is promiſed to the Jewes, and not only to
them, but to us Gentiles, who <hi>ſometimes <pb n="175" facs="tcp:871:98"/>were afar
off;</hi> not to this Gentile or that, but to all that are prickt in heart for
the want of him. <hi>For the promiſe is to you and to your children, and to
all that are afar off.</hi> Let every one therefore upon this ground, that
feels his ſpirit prickt and wounded, for want of Chriſt, take words to
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and go unto God, and ſay. O God, my ſoule is a poore
Chriſtleſſe ſoule. I ſinde by wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full experience, that the Lord
Jeſus is not with my ſpirit, by reaſon of which I live wickedly to thy
diſhonour, and ſhall, I know not how ſoone, die miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably, to mine own
eternall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing, if thou do not ſhew mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon me, according to thy
promiſe. Thou haſt ſaid that thou wilt beſtow Chriſt, grace and
ſalvation, upon them that are afar off; make good thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious promiſe to
mee, whoſe <pb n="176" facs="tcp:871:99"/>ſpirit is far from Chriſt, grace and all
good; ſo ſhalt thou ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige me for ever unto thee; and I ſhall tell of
thy goodneſſe as long as I live.</p>
            <p>Having thus ſpoken what I thought fit, to ſuch as finde by
what was formerly delivered, that Chriſt is not with their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; I
ſhall in the next place ſpeak unto you, that by what was formerly
delivered, finde, that Chriſt is indeed with your ſpirits. Something by way
of counſell, and ſome thing by way of conſolation, I have to deliver unto
you. Three things by way of counſell, I would commend unto you:
<hi>thankefully acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge this great favour; carefully preſerve it; and
induſtriouſly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to augment it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, thankfully acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge this great favour. 'Tis a pearle
of great price, that God <pb n="177" facs="tcp:871:99"/>hath caſt into thy boſome, to
give Chriſt to bee with thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: and for great favours, every one will
acknowledge it very fit, and juſt, that they ſhould bee thankfull. 'Tis a
Jewell that Chriſt ſcarce gives to one of ten-thouſand: and for rare
gifts, every one will readily confeſſe it to bee great ingratitude, not
thankefully to acknowledge them. Doeſt thou not heare ſome ſweare, ſome
curſe, ſome lye, like their father the Devill? Why thou wouldſt have
beene ſuch an one, had not God given Chriſt to be with thy ſpirit.
Doeſt thou not ſee ſome drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, ſome whoremaſters, ſome
murderers, ſome perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors of the Saints? Why thou would'ſt have beene
ſuch in one, if God had not given Chriſt to be with thy ſpirit. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
thou not ſee ſome make a <pb n="178" facs="tcp:871:100"/>God of their belly, ſome
make a God of their wealth, ſome proud, ſome mad, ſome putting far from
them the evill day, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving as if they ſhould never dye? Why, thou wouldeſt
have been ſuch an one, had not God given Chriſt to be with thy ſpirit.
Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou not ſee ſome <hi>Nabals,</hi> ſome <hi>Iezabels,</hi>
ſome <hi>Caines,</hi> ſome <hi>Demaſes,</hi> ſome <hi>Iudaſes?</hi>
Why, amongſt the number of theſe wouldeſt thou have beene, had not God
given Chriſt to be with thy ſpirit. Wherefore magnifie the Lord with all
thy might, and let all that is within thee praiſe his holy Name. Think but
how it was with thee, when thy ſpirit was without Chriſt. How <hi>fooliſh
thou waſt ſerving divers luſts:</hi> how the God of this world which
rules mightily in the children of diſobedience, did rule mightily in thee.
How weak thy ſpirit <pb n="179" facs="tcp:871:100"/>was, and eaſily overcome and
carried captive of every luſt. How drunken thy ſpirit was, and reeld from
one opinion to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; one day thou thoughtſt thus, and thus, and another
day thou thoughtſt quite contrary. I ſay, do but think of theſe things,
and how the Lord might juſtly have left thee ſtill, to have gone on thus,
untill thou hadſt peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, as he hath done many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands; and then be
unthankfull, for the communion of Chriſt with thy ſpirit, if thou canſt.
It was this conſideration that ſet <hi>Paul</hi> a wondring at the
goodneſs of the Lord. <hi>I was a blaſphemer, a perſecutor, &amp;c. yet I
obtained mercy.</hi> He circumflexes this term <hi>[I] yet [I] obtained
mercy,</hi> &amp;c. It was wonderfull in his eye, that God ſhould give
Chriſt, to dwell with ſuch a bloody blaſpheming ſpirit, as he had. In
this way let <pb n="180" facs="tcp:871:101"/>us go to work, to raiſe our dull
ſpirits, to magnifie the free goodneſſe of the Lord: for 'tis a worke of
all workes, that God loves. I was a man of a very proud, paſſionate,
malicious, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane ſpirit; and yet I obtained mercy. God hath given
Chriſt to be with this depraved ſpirit, and in a little time he hath done
very much, and made a manifeſt change in my ſpirit; of very proud, he hath
made it in ſome meaſure humble; of very paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate, in ſome
meaſure patient; of very malicious, in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure loving; of very
uncleane, in ſome meaſure continent. O! the riches of his love; <hi>how
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable is his mercy, and his love paſt finding out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, as I would have you thankfully acknowledge this great
favour, ſo I would have you carefully labour to preſerve 
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:871:101"/>it. You find that you have Chriſt with your ſpirits,
take heed you do not loſe him. Thou wert bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter loſe thy life, then loſe
the ſpeciall preſence of Chriſt with thy ſpirit. 'Tis a prime and
prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall bleſſing, as thou haſt heard; a bleſſing of more worth then
this world; nay of more worth then thy ſoule, which Chriſt va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lues above
the world. Now choice things, we are uſually ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry carefull of, and keepe
them choicely. Chriſt totally (I know) can no man loſe, which hath him
after a ſpeciall manner, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with his ſpirit: but accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to
ſome prime &amp; principall operations, he may: according to others, very
far, though not totally. A man may loſe the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſt with his
ſpirit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally, as a Comforter. <hi>The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, which ſhould relieve
my ſoule is far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> in the 
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:871:102"/>perſon of the afflicted Church.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.16</note> 'Tis probable enough, that
<hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> ſpirit, was thus ſtript of Chriſt, by his dolorous
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, which frequently wee reade of. <hi>Is his mercy cleane gone for
ever? doth his promiſe faile for evermore? Hath God forgotten to be gracious?
hath he in anger ſhut up his tender mercies? Will the Lord caſt off for
ever? and will he be favourable no more?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.7,8,9.</note> Some carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages in Chriſtians
towards Chriſt, make Chriſt totally alter his carriage towards the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; though
for his promiſe ſake, he will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver totally remove himſelfe from
them.</p>
            <p>As when Chriſtians doe not keep their watch ſtrictly againſt
ſinne, in all the occaſions of it; then Chriſt inſtead of being a
Comforter, becomes a convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer; and inſtead of ſpeaking ſweet things,
hee ſpeakes very <pb n="183" facs="tcp:871:102"/>bitter unto the ſoule. This was the
caſe of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Peter.</hi> Or when Chriſtians are
careleſſe, and ſluggiſh, to maintaine and encreaſe their ſweet
Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with Chriſt; unyeelding to the ſweet motions of the ſpirit of
Chriſt, and turning oft times the deafe eare, againſt the ſtill voice
behind them, which ſaith, <hi>this is the way, walke in it.</hi> Then
Chriſt drawes a curtaine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the ſpirit of man, and himſelfe, and
leaves the ſpirit of man in the darke, and full of feares. This is notably
illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by that language of the Spouſe, <hi>It is the voyce of my
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved that knocketh, ſaying, open to me, my Siſter, my Love, my Dove, my
underfiled: for my head is filled with dew, and my locks with the drops of the
night.</hi> The Church was convinced of this, that it was her beloved,
ſeeking neerer <pb n="184" facs="tcp:871:103"/>communion with her, and yet obſerve
how ſhe replyes. <hi>I have put off my coat, how ſhall I put it on? I have
waſhed my feet, how ſhall I defile them? I opened to my beloved, but my
beloved had withdrawne himſelfe and was gone; my ſoule failed when he
ſpake; I ſought him, but I could not finde him: I called him, but he gave
me no anſwer.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.</note> You that finde
the preſence of Chriſt with your ſpirits, as a Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, make
Chriſtian uſe of what I have ſaid, that you may ſtill enjoy ſo great
a mercy. And if you loſe the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, as a Comforter to your
ſpirits, miſerable comforters will all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things prove unto you. You
will mourne, and none will bee able to comfort you, if Chriſt as a Comforter
forſake your ſpirits.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as a leader, a man may very far loſe the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of
Chriſt with his ſpirit. As if <pb n="185" facs="tcp:871:103"/>a Chriſtian take
liberty to ſinne againſt that light, which Chriſt hath ſet up in his
ſpirit; this will make Chriſt firſt or laſt (if not timely lookt unto)
leave a man to his owne underſtanding, to ſteare his courſe; and then
will ſuch a man declare himſelfe quickly, to be a foole, and a beaſt, in
many points, as <hi>David</hi> ſaith. Have you not ſeene Chriſtians of
great light, erre injudgement, and erre in practiſe? Whence comes this
weakneſſe, but from hence, that Chriſt as a leader ſtands aloofe from
their ſpirits? which is a plaine demonſtration that a man may loſe the
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſt with his ſpirit, as a leader. <hi>David</hi> (I
beleeve) found the truth of this, as well as of the former, by wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
experience. A man may col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect ſo much cleerely, from his owne words.
<hi>Caſt mee not away <pb n="186" facs="tcp:871:104"/>from thy preſence, and take not
thy holy ſpirit from me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.11</note>
The Spirit of God is therefore called by <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> a <hi>holy</hi>
Spirit, becauſe holy in himſelfe (the Spirit of the holy God, as hee ſaid
to <hi>Daniel</hi>) but principally here, as I conceive, <hi>Abofficio:</hi>
becauſe the worker of holineſſe in us. <hi>David</hi> doubtleſſe by
his fall, found an exceeding weakneſſe in his Spirit, unto all good, over
what formerly hee did; and a ſtrong propenſity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to erre; as every
act of ſin leaves ſeed and ſpawn upon the ſpirit, to bring forth more,
to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the firſt, or to commit the like againe. But more then all this, he
found Chriſt to ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loofe from his ſpirit; not exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing that
ſpeciall dominion in his ſpirit, as before, for the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing of luſt,
and ſuggeſting of holy motions and deſires, but leaving him as it were to
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <pb n="187" facs="tcp:871:104"/>as one with whom hee would have no more to
do. And therefore doth <hi>David</hi> ſo dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully complaine, <hi>Caſt me
not away from thy preſence, and take not thy [holy] Spirit from me:</hi> you
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which finde Chriſt with your ſpirits, as a tender leader, take
heed of ſinning againſt any part of that light, which he ſets up in your
underſtandings, or againſt any motions of his ſpirit, which he
ſuggeſts unto you; leſt he leave you to your own light, and to your own
ſtrength, and then will you run from leſſe ſins to greater, from one
ſin to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, like <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> to the
ſcandalizing of the Goſpell, and the deſperate wounding of your own
ſoules.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt thing that I would commend unto you, by way
of counſell, is this, labour to augment this great favour. 
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:871:105"/>You finde Chriſt with your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, labour
induſtriouſly, to have Chriſt more and more with your ſpirits. 'Tis a
prime and principall bleſſing, as you have heard, to have Chriſt with
your ſpirits; therefore labour to get as much of this favour &amp;
happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe as poſſibly you can. Thou haſt Chriſt with thy ſpirit
as a teacher; why thou maiſt have him yet more intimate with thee, and open
unto thee, in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting divine myſteries, if thou <hi>follow on to
know,</hi> as the Prophet ſpeaks, if thou humbly forget, &amp; look over all
thou haſt, &amp; preſſe hard after more: the things thou knoweſt not,
Chriſt will teach thy ſpirit, morning by morning, as by the learned.
Chriſt hath taught thy ſpirit many truths; why, he will <hi>leade thy
ſpirit into all truth,</hi> if thou urge his promiſe and beleeve. He will
<hi>fill thee with <pb n="189" facs="tcp:871:105"/>the knowledge of his will in all
wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and ſpirituall underſtanding,</hi> If thou pray for it as
<hi>Paul</hi> did for the <hi>Coloſſians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou findeſt Chriſt with thy ſpirit as a Comforter; why thou
maiſt have yet much more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation from him, if thou ſtudy to be more
pliable to him. Thou haſt Chriſt diſtilling drops of conſolation into
thy ſpirit, now and then; why thou maiſt have Chriſt powring in flagons
of love into thy ſoule, filling thee with joy unſpeakable and full of
glory, if thou bring thy ſpirit to bee more lowly and meek; for ſuch find
moſt <hi>reſt to their ſoules:</hi> if thou carefully keep <hi>comming to
Chriſt ſtill,</hi> in every preſſure of ſpirit; for ſuch finde
moſt <hi>eaſe:</hi> that is renewing faith ſtill, as thou reneweſt thy
ſins.</p>
            <p>Thou findeſt Chriſt with thy ſpirit, as a quickner &amp;
ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <pb n="190" facs="tcp:871:106"/>to duty; why thou maiſt find him yet
more mighty with thy ſpirit this way, if thou powre out thy ſpirit often
with <hi>David</hi> for quickning grace; and if thou more deny thine own
ſtrength, and caſt thy ſelf more upon his. Could we but attain
<hi>Pauls</hi> height in ſelfe-denyall, to bee nothing in our ſelvs
(<hi>though I am nothing,</hi> ſaith he)<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi>
12.11.</note> we ſhould finde Chriſt gloriouſly preſent ſtill with
our ſpirits, and be more conſtant in zeale &amp; ſtrength to every good
work, then we are. I conclude this thus, bee ſo tractable to Chriſt, that
thou maiſt with <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> winne upon Chriſt ſtill; and think that
thou canſt never bee neere enough to him, nor inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate enough with him; and
this is the ready way, to have a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven upon earth: for the more we get
Chriſt to be with our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, the more truly may wee bee ſaid to be in
Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="191" facs="tcp:871:106"/>The laſt thing that I have to ſay to
you, that find Chriſt with your ſpirits, is matter of conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. Here
is comfort for you againſt famine. When thy body wants food, Chriſt that is
with thy ſpirit, will give that meat to eat, which the world knowes not off;
ſo that when others re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine, and <hi>curſe God and their King</hi> in their
extremity, as the Prophet ſpeaks; thou ſhalt bee patient in this
tribulation, and inſtant in prayer to him, who can command Ravens to bring
thee bread and fleſh to feed on; and will, rather then thou ſhalt ſtarve,
if thy life may bee more to his glory, then thy death.</p>
            <p>Here's comfort for you againſt the ſword. In the midſt of
all troubles and fears, Chriſt that is with thy ſpirit will beare thee up
admirably. What is the face of an enemy to terrifie, if Chriſt 
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:871:107"/>be with thy ſpirit. What is the ſpoiling of thy
goods? nay what is the ſpoiling of thy body? if Chriſt bee with thy
ſoule. A Mountaine of miſery, is but as a Mole-hill, if Chriſt ſupport
the ſpirit. To think of the Sword is a naked reference to fleſh and blood,
and ſo nothing is more terrible: but let us that feare the Loro think of it,
in reference to Chriſt that is with our ſpirits, &amp; then wee ſhall not
be troubled, though we heare of warres and rumours of warres, no more then at
the rumours of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther calamity.</p>
            <p>Here is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort for you againſt the Plague, which is here and
there ſcatterd in the Kingdome. What is any diſeaſe to the body, if
Chriſt bee with thy ſoule? As the outward man decayeth, the inward man
ſhall be renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed daily, becauſe Chriſt is with <pb n="193" facs="tcp:871:107"/>thy
ſpirit. When thy body is full of paine, thy ſoule ſhall be full of
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, becauſe Chriſt is with thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. When thy body is ſealed
with ſpots for death, thy ſoule ſhall be ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the Holy Ghoſt
unto eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, becauſe Chriſt is with thy ſpirit. The plague of the
body is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, if this plague of plagues bee not upon the ſpirit, to wit,
deſtitute of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Here is comfort for you againſt perſecution. When men frowne
up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee without, Chriſt will ſmile upon thy ſpirit within: when men
lade thy outward man w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, Chriſt will fill thy inward man with
comforts: when men ſhut up thy body from the communion of Saints, Chriſt
will give thy ſpirit a large freedome of communion with himſelf. When men
ſtrike thy body, Chriſt will ſtroke thy ſoule: when men kill thy body,
Chriſt will ſave thy ſoule. In a word, as the afflictions 
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:871:108"/>of Chriſt abound in thy body, ſo the conſolations
of Chriſt ſhall abound in thy ſoule, becauſe Chriſt is with thy
ſpirit. Name any miſery that is incident to man, and here's comfort to be
ſuckt out of this point, to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe unto it. Finally in life, in death,
&amp; eternally after death, Chriſt that is with thy ſpirit will be gaine
unto thee. Thy life he will make comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table; thy death hopefull; and thy
being after death eternally joyfull. Wherefore I will conclude my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon for
the good of you, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth his Epiſtle for the good of
<hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy, The Lord Ieſus Chriſt bee with your ſpirits.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>Trinuni Deo gloria.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Pro <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, leg.
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. pag. 7. For <hi>ſay,</hi> read
<hi>ſaw,</hi> p. 39. l. 6. pro <hi>pereunte ſolep, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nt omnia,</hi> lege, <hi>pereunte ſole pereunt
omnia.</hi> p. 114. Marg. For <hi>I do conceive,</hi> r. <hi>I do not
conceive.</hi> p. 169. l. 7.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:871:108"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
